In this course, you have seen a lot of
In this course, you have seen a lot of different kinds of uh uses of LLMs. And
different kinds of uh uses of LLMs. And
different kinds of uh uses of LLMs. And today, I'm going to emphasize the use of
today, I'm going to emphasize the use of
today, I'm going to emphasize the use of LLMs as a tool of scientific and
LLMs as a tool of scientific and
LLMs as a tool of scientific and mathematical discovery. And in
mathematical discovery. And in
mathematical discovery. And in particular, there's going to be an
particular, there's going to be an
particular, there's going to be an emphasis on the ability of LLMs to
emphasis on the ability of LLMs to
emphasis on the ability of LLMs to discover abstract concepts and how this
discover abstract concepts and how this
discover abstract concepts and how this can accelerate these uh discovery
can accelerate these uh discovery
can accelerate these uh discovery processes. Okay. So uh let us dive in.
processes. Okay. So uh let us dive in.
processes. Okay. So uh let us dive in. Let us start with u the problem of
Let us start with u the problem of
Let us start with u the problem of mathematical discovery. This is of
mathematical discovery. This is of
mathematical discovery. This is of course one of the grandest challenges uh
course one of the grandest challenges uh
course one of the grandest challenges uh known to
known to
known to humanity. Now um how does the process of
humanity. Now um how does the process of
humanity. Now um how does the process of mathematical discovery look like? There
mathematical discovery look like? There
mathematical discovery look like? There is the p the the process of modeling
is the p the the process of modeling
is the p the the process of modeling where you are you know getting inspired
where you are you know getting inspired
where you are you know getting inspired by some sort of a real world phenomenon
by some sort of a real world phenomenon
by some sort of a real world phenomenon and then modeling it uh in terms of a
and then modeling it uh in terms of a
and then modeling it uh in terms of a variety of definitions and and concepts.
variety of definitions and and concepts.
variety of definitions and and concepts. Now once you have a set of definitions
Now once you have a set of definitions
Now once you have a set of definitions at that point you may want to
at that point you may want to
at that point you may want to conjecture various properties of these
conjecture various properties of these
conjecture various properties of these definitions and then these are u you
definitions and then these are u you
definitions and then these are u you know potentially candidate theorems and
know potentially candidate theorems and
know potentially candidate theorems and lemas and then there is this process of
lemas and then there is this process of
lemas and then there is this process of rigorous reasoning where you are
rigorous reasoning where you are
rigorous reasoning where you are actually proving these statements and
actually proving these statements and
actually proving these statements and this process is for human
this process is for human
this process is for human mathematicians intrinsically social. you
mathematicians intrinsically social. you
mathematicians intrinsically social. you are convincing each other about the the
are convincing each other about the the
are convincing each other about the the rigor of your reasoning and the value of
rigor of your reasoning and the value of
rigor of your reasoning and the value of your conjectures, right? But this
your conjectures, right? But this
your conjectures, right? But this process just continues in this sort of
process just continues in this sort of
process just continues in this sort of an iterative loop. Uh so you may have
an iterative loop. Uh so you may have
an iterative loop. Uh so you may have you may see proofs and counter examples
you may see proofs and counter examples
you may see proofs and counter examples and these may influence your models as
and these may influence your models as
and these may influence your models as well as your conjectures and this
well as your conjectures and this
well as your conjectures and this process just goes on. Right? That's how
process just goes on. Right? That's how
process just goes on. Right? That's how the the um that's the history of
the the um that's the history of
the the um that's the history of mathematics.
mathematics.
mathematics. Now the dream of the field of AI for
Now the dream of the field of AI for
Now the dream of the field of AI for math is that you want to automate uh
math is that you want to automate uh
math is that you want to automate uh substantial pieces of this process and
substantial pieces of this process and
substantial pieces of this process and as a result you want to accelerate this
as a result you want to accelerate this
as a result you want to accelerate this process even more. You want to be able
process even more. You want to be able
process even more. You want to be able to discover new kinds of math and um and
to discover new kinds of math and um and
to discover new kinds of math and um and uh you know uh this includes settling
uh you know uh this includes settling
uh you know uh this includes settling known conjectures but also potentially
known conjectures but also potentially
known conjectures but also potentially coming up with new
coming up with new
coming up with new conjectures. And then there is the the
conjectures. And then there is the the
conjectures. And then there is the the setting of natural sciences that is also
setting of natural sciences that is also
setting of natural sciences that is also going to be something I'll cover in this
going to be something I'll cover in this
going to be something I'll cover in this lecture. And here uh unlike in math you
lecture. And here uh unlike in math you
lecture. And here uh unlike in math you are engaging with the real
are engaging with the real
are engaging with the real world. There is this process of theory
world. There is this process of theory
world. There is this process of theory building where you're coming up with
building where you're coming up with
building where you're coming up with hypothesis about the the universe and
hypothesis about the the universe and
hypothesis about the the universe and then you are using uh these hypothesis
then you are using uh these hypothesis
then you are using uh these hypothesis to design experiments and then you are
to design experiments and then you are
to design experiments and then you are experimentally validating them right and
experimentally validating them right and
experimentally validating them right and this experimental validation process
this experimental validation process
this experimental validation process creates new data and then this data
creates new data and then this data
creates new data and then this data leads to new kinds of theories uh for
leads to new kinds of theories uh for
leads to new kinds of theories uh for example by refinement of the existing
example by refinement of the existing
example by refinement of the existing hypothesis or in some cases you may want
hypothesis or in some cases you may want
hypothesis or in some cases you may want to just come up with entirely new
to just come up with entirely new
to just come up with entirely new concepts and and um new
concepts and and um new
concepts and and um new predictions. So the ambition of the area
predictions. So the ambition of the area
predictions. So the ambition of the area of AI for science is to automate
of AI for science is to automate
of AI for science is to automate hypothesis generation and experiment
hypothesis generation and experiment
hypothesis generation and experiment design.
design.
design. Now the key ideas in the areas of AI for
Now the key ideas in the areas of AI for
Now the key ideas in the areas of AI for math and AI for science at this point
math and AI for science at this point
math and AI for science at this point are that number one search is a really
are that number one search is a really
are that number one search is a really powerful concept and so we want to
powerful concept and so we want to
powerful concept and so we want to imagine these uh spaces of hypothesis
imagine these uh spaces of hypothesis
imagine these uh spaces of hypothesis conjectures and proofs and
conjectures and proofs and
conjectures and proofs and systematically search
systematically search
systematically search them. Now uh this is of course a very
them. Now uh this is of course a very
them. Now uh this is of course a very massive space. There are all
massive space. There are all
massive space. There are all these you know uh potential statements
these you know uh potential statements
these you know uh potential statements about various mathematical objects and
about various mathematical objects and
about various mathematical objects and there are all these hypotheses that are
there are all these hypotheses that are
there are all these hypotheses that are possible in the universe and this space
possible in the universe and this space
possible in the universe and this space is you know clearly infinite. Now um how
is you know clearly infinite. Now um how
is you know clearly infinite. Now um how do you explore this space in a in a
do you explore this space in a in a
do you explore this space in a in a tractable way? Well, you use prior
tractable way? Well, you use prior
tractable way? Well, you use prior knowledge to prioritize directions of
knowledge to prioritize directions of
knowledge to prioritize directions of search. And that's also how humans
search. And that's also how humans
search. And that's also how humans proceed. We don't just do discovery in a
proceed. We don't just do discovery in a
proceed. We don't just do discovery in a vacuum. We
vacuum. We
vacuum. We read existing papers and uh sometimes we
read existing papers and uh sometimes we
read existing papers and uh sometimes we incrementally advance on them and
incrementally advance on them and
incrementally advance on them and sometimes we make a big leap. But that
sometimes we make a big leap. But that
sometimes we make a big leap. But that prior knowledge is always of
prior knowledge is always of
prior knowledge is always of value. But then also we learn from
value. But then also we learn from
value. But then also we learn from experience how and how not to uh do this
experience how and how not to uh do this
experience how and how not to uh do this sort of
sort of
sort of exploration. You know you find out that
exploration. You know you find out that
exploration. You know you find out that you made certain uh choices uh while
you made certain uh choices uh while
you made certain uh choices uh while building your theory and then you find
building your theory and then you find
building your theory and then you find that this just didn't work right. And
that this just didn't work right. And
that this just didn't work right. And that's experience for you. And then you
that's experience for you. And then you
that's experience for you. And then you use this experience to potentially take
use this experience to potentially take
use this experience to potentially take completely new
completely new
completely new directions. And then another piece that
directions. And then another piece that
directions. And then another piece that is very important uh has been very
is very important uh has been very
is very important uh has been very important through the history of math
important through the history of math
important through the history of math and science has been to discover
and science has been to discover
and science has been to discover abstract concepts and tools. Uh so for
abstract concepts and tools. Uh so for
abstract concepts and tools. Uh so for example you know the idea of calculus
example you know the idea of calculus
example you know the idea of calculus that really sped up the progress of
that really sped up the progress of
that really sped up the progress of science uh after it was invented. Uh
science uh after it was invented. Uh
science uh after it was invented. Uh similarly with algebra and and uh really
similarly with algebra and and uh really
similarly with algebra and and uh really all major branches of mathematics uh
all major branches of mathematics uh
all major branches of mathematics uh came from the need to abstract some sort
came from the need to abstract some sort
came from the need to abstract some sort of uh real world process. And then the
of uh real world process. And then the
of uh real world process. And then the value of these abstractions is that that
value of these abstractions is that that
value of these abstractions is that that they speed up both this process of
they speed up both this process of
they speed up both this process of exploration and also this learning
exploration and also this learning
exploration and also this learning process that I previously
process that I previously
process that I previously mentioned. Now if you think of it,
mentioned. Now if you think of it,
mentioned. Now if you think of it, LLM bring something to the uh table
LLM bring something to the uh table
LLM bring something to the uh table regarding each of these uh criteria. So
regarding each of these uh criteria. So
regarding each of these uh criteria. So for example uh you know if you're doing
for example uh you know if you're doing
for example uh you know if you're doing a search in a in a very large space of
a search in a in a very large space of
a search in a in a very large space of potential scientific hypothesis and LLM
potential scientific hypothesis and LLM
potential scientific hypothesis and LLM has inside it a lot of knowledge about
has inside it a lot of knowledge about
has inside it a lot of knowledge about uh what sort of hypothesis have
uh what sort of hypothesis have
uh what sort of hypothesis have historically tended to work in science.
historically tended to work in science.
historically tended to work in science. And so this knowledge can um potentially
And so this knowledge can um potentially
And so this knowledge can um potentially help you um direct this search
help you um direct this search
help you um direct this search process. And then also um you know uh in
process. And then also um you know uh in
process. And then also um you know uh in this course uh you have seen examples of
this course uh you have seen examples of
this course uh you have seen examples of LLM agents and in this class you're
LLM agents and in this class you're
LLM agents and in this class you're going to see more of this. Uh so these
going to see more of this. Uh so these
going to see more of this. Uh so these are systems that contain inside them
are systems that contain inside them
are systems that contain inside them LLMs as modules but they're also
LLMs as modules but they're also
LLMs as modules but they're also interacting with the world and they're
interacting with the world and they're
interacting with the world and they're learning from experience and and this
learning from experience and and this
learning from experience and and this experience is uh gathered as as data and
experience is uh gathered as as data and
experience is uh gathered as as data and then often uh stuck into the prompt but
then often uh stuck into the prompt but
then often uh stuck into the prompt but sometimes you can even do reinforcement
sometimes you can even do reinforcement
sometimes you can even do reinforcement learning or other kinds of you know
learning or other kinds of you know
learning or other kinds of you know modification of the LLM weights. uh but
modification of the LLM weights. uh but
modification of the LLM weights. uh but the point is that there are all these
the point is that there are all these
the point is that there are all these established methods for doing learning
established methods for doing learning
established methods for doing learning combined with uh the use of language
combined with uh the use of language
combined with uh the use of language models and that is something that we can
models and that is something that we can
models and that is something that we can exploit here as
exploit here as
exploit here as well. Now the use of LLMs for
well. Now the use of LLMs for
well. Now the use of LLMs for abstraction this is something that's not
abstraction this is something that's not
abstraction this is something that's not uh well explored yet. This is a really
uh well explored yet. This is a really
uh well explored yet. This is a really new idea but I'm going to give you some
new idea but I'm going to give you some
new idea but I'm going to give you some evidence um as to why there might be a
evidence um as to why there might be a
evidence um as to why there might be a lot of things going on here.
lot of things going on here.
lot of things going on here. And uh there is certainly a lot more to
And uh there is certainly a lot more to
And uh there is certainly a lot more to be done about the use of LLMs in uh
be done about the use of LLMs in uh
be done about the use of LLMs in uh constructing new concepts and new
constructing new concepts and new
constructing new concepts and new tools. So I think that u LLM
tools. So I think that u LLM
tools. So I think that u LLM agents have tremendous promise in
agents have tremendous promise in
agents have tremendous promise in mathematical and scientific discovery.
mathematical and scientific discovery.
mathematical and scientific discovery. And the reason is that uh the the so far
And the reason is that uh the the so far
And the reason is that uh the the so far as all of these these um ideas go LLM
as all of these these um ideas go LLM
as all of these these um ideas go LLM have a potential to contribute um in in
have a potential to contribute um in in
have a potential to contribute um in in uh with regards to
each. So this may all seem somewhat
each. So this may all seem somewhat abstract. So I'm going to now jump into
abstract. So I'm going to now jump into
abstract. So I'm going to now jump into some concrete results. And this lecture
some concrete results. And this lecture
some concrete results. And this lecture is divided into two pieces. In the first
is divided into two pieces. In the first
is divided into two pieces. In the first part, we are going to talk about AI for
part, we are going to talk about AI for
part, we are going to talk about AI for mathematical discovery. And then in the
mathematical discovery. And then in the
mathematical discovery. And then in the second part, we are going to talk about
second part, we are going to talk about
second part, we are going to talk about AI for scientific discovery. And in each
AI for scientific discovery. And in each
AI for scientific discovery. And in each of these cases, I'm going to show
of these cases, I'm going to show
of these cases, I'm going to show you some um LLM agents built using quite
you some um LLM agents built using quite
you some um LLM agents built using quite different algorithms. But uh but we'll
different algorithms. But uh but we'll
different algorithms. But uh but we'll see that uh these agents
see that uh these agents
see that uh these agents realize many of these ideas that we
realize many of these ideas that we
realize many of these ideas that we talked about in the previous
talked about in the previous
talked about in the previous slide. Okay. So let's talk about AI for
slide. Okay. So let's talk about AI for
slide. Okay. So let's talk about AI for math. Over the last few years, there's
math. Over the last few years, there's
math. Over the last few years, there's been tremendous interest in this field.
been tremendous interest in this field.
been tremendous interest in this field. Here's Terry Tao from 2023 talking about
Here's Terry Tao from 2023 talking about
Here's Terry Tao from 2023 talking about how AI from that year can already
how AI from that year can already
how AI from that year can already generate suggestive hints and uh help
generate suggestive hints and uh help
generate suggestive hints and uh help with the mathematical process. And he
with the mathematical process. And he
with the mathematical process. And he predicted that by
predicted that by
predicted that by 2026 AI can become a trustworthy
2026 AI can become a trustworthy
2026 AI can become a trustworthy co-author in math research papers and in
co-author in math research papers and in
co-author in math research papers and in other fields as well.
other fields as well.
other fields as well. Now uh 2026 is not yet here but I would
Now uh 2026 is not yet here but I would
Now uh 2026 is not yet here but I would say that uh this prediction seems very
say that uh this prediction seems very
say that uh this prediction seems very plausible as of
plausible as of
plausible as of now. Now um in terms of concrete
now. Now um in terms of concrete
now. Now um in terms of concrete systems 01 when it was introduced um one
systems 01 when it was introduced um one
systems 01 when it was introduced um one of
of
of the highlights was that it did really
the highlights was that it did really
the highlights was that it did really well in various uh competition
well in various uh competition
well in various uh competition mathematics problems. So um here is a
mathematics problems. So um here is a
mathematics problems. So um here is a plot. It shows how 01 does compared to
plot. It shows how 01 does compared to
plot. It shows how 01 does compared to GBD40. And as you see, accuracy in this
GBD40. And as you see, accuracy in this
GBD40. And as you see, accuracy in this particular competition AM 2024 uh has uh
particular competition AM 2024 uh has uh
particular competition AM 2024 uh has uh gone up very
gone up very
gone up very substantially. And then of course last
substantially. And then of course last
substantially. And then of course last year my colleagues at Google DeepMind,
year my colleagues at Google DeepMind,
year my colleagues at Google DeepMind, they built this system that uh achieved
they built this system that uh achieved
they built this system that uh achieved silver medal level performance at the
silver medal level performance at the
silver medal level performance at the IMO. And uh you have already heard us
IMO. And uh you have already heard us
IMO. And uh you have already heard us talk about that uh in this course. So
talk about that uh in this course. So
talk about that uh in this course. So I'm not going to uh go into further
I'm not going to uh go into further
I'm not going to uh go into further detail or too much more detail about
detail or too much more detail about
detail or too much more detail about that in this talk but uh you you know
that in this talk but uh you you know
that in this talk but uh you you know that uh it's it's impressive and it uses
that uh it's it's impressive and it uses
that uh it's it's impressive and it uses a lot of very impressive
machinery. Now one question that uh I
machinery. Now one question that uh I think is important to ask is that is it
think is important to ask is that is it
think is important to ask is that is it all going to be done just with LLMs?
In other words, you know, do you need
In other words, you know, do you need any sort of um you know, additional
any sort of um you know, additional
any sort of um you know, additional machinery uh that uh combines LLM with,
machinery uh that uh combines LLM with,
machinery uh that uh combines LLM with, for example, actions? You know, this is
for example, actions? You know, this is
for example, actions? You know, this is really the characteristic that
really the characteristic that
really the characteristic that distinguishes LLM agents from just uh
distinguishes LLM agents from just uh
distinguishes LLM agents from just uh basic
basic
basic LLMs. And uh so I would say that um you
LLMs. And uh so I would say that um you
LLMs. And uh so I would say that um you know there are certainly still believers
know there are certainly still believers
know there are certainly still believers uh in the potential of just LLMs alone
uh in the potential of just LLMs alone
uh in the potential of just LLMs alone to do everything uh after being trained
to do everything uh after being trained
to do everything uh after being trained on
on
on language. But um I am personally a
language. But um I am personally a
language. But um I am personally a little bit skeptical about that
little bit skeptical about that
little bit skeptical about that possibility. Now that said you know one
possibility. Now that said you know one
possibility. Now that said you know one must admit that over the last couple of
must admit that over the last couple of
must admit that over the last couple of years just LLMs have come a long way. Uh
years just LLMs have come a long way. Uh
years just LLMs have come a long way. Uh so here is the picture of how you train
so here is the picture of how you train
so here is the picture of how you train an LLM on on u uh for these sorts of
an LLM on on u uh for these sorts of
an LLM on on u uh for these sorts of mathematical settings. So you're going
mathematical settings. So you're going
mathematical settings. So you're going to start with a pre-trained LLM. Then
to start with a pre-trained LLM. Then
to start with a pre-trained LLM. Then you're going to train it on you know
you're going to train it on you know
you're going to train it on you know math related web docs and then you know
math related web docs and then you know
math related web docs and then you know uh problems with step-by-step solutions,
uh problems with step-by-step solutions,
uh problems with step-by-step solutions, problems with tool integrated solutions
problems with tool integrated solutions
problems with tool integrated solutions and so on and so forth. And then
and so on and so forth. And then
and so on and so forth. And then ultimately you have this LLM that can
ultimately you have this LLM that can
ultimately you have this LLM that can use for example Python APIs and that can
use for example Python APIs and that can
use for example Python APIs and that can solve math problems.
solve math problems.
solve math problems. And this has again as I said uh come a
And this has again as I said uh come a
And this has again as I said uh come a long way. Uh so for example here is a
long way. Uh so for example here is a
long way. Uh so for example here is a problem from the partner math
problem from the partner math
problem from the partner math competition from last year and 01's
competition from last year and 01's
competition from last year and 01's response on this problem is actually
response on this problem is actually
response on this problem is actually very reasonable.
very reasonable.
very reasonable. uh and uh as these systems are getting
uh and uh as these systems are getting
uh and uh as these systems are getting better and
better and
better and better, it seems like they're solving
better, it seems like they're solving
better, it seems like they're solving more and more problems uh that are of
more and more problems uh that are of
more and more problems uh that are of this uh nature that are similarly hard
this uh nature that are similarly hard
this uh nature that are similarly hard or or
or or
or or harder. But that said, there is a there
harder. But that said, there is a there
harder. But that said, there is a there are some fundamental weaknesses of this
are some fundamental weaknesses of this
are some fundamental weaknesses of this neural only approach uh that you'd get
neural only approach uh that you'd get
neural only approach uh that you'd get with just a basic LLM.
with just a basic LLM.
with just a basic LLM. And the reason is that um or one
And the reason is that um or one
And the reason is that um or one fundamental reason is that there is this
fundamental reason is that there is this
fundamental reason is that there is this issue of data
issue of data
issue of data scarcity. In order to do rigorous
scarcity. In order to do rigorous
scarcity. In order to do rigorous mathematical reasoning, not just
mathematical reasoning, not just
mathematical reasoning, not just computing answers to wellposed
computing answers to wellposed
computing answers to wellposed questions, you need to have a lot of
questions, you need to have a lot of
questions, you need to have a lot of highquality traces of uh mathematical
highquality traces of uh mathematical
highquality traces of uh mathematical reasoning or alternatively you would
reasoning or alternatively you would
reasoning or alternatively you would need highquality reward functions. And
need highquality reward functions. And
need highquality reward functions. And this is difficult to get just with human
this is difficult to get just with human
this is difficult to get just with human produced
produced
produced data beyond high school or competition
data beyond high school or competition
data beyond high school or competition settings. And then a second reason
settings. And then a second reason
settings. And then a second reason fundamentally is that natural language
fundamentally is that natural language
fundamentally is that natural language reasoning is hard to verify. And this is
reasoning is hard to verify. And this is
reasoning is hard to verify. And this is something that is um that is uh a
something that is um that is uh a
something that is um that is uh a fundamental weakness of this language
fundamental weakness of this language
fundamental weakness of this language only
only
only models. And there are even settings
models. And there are even settings
models. And there are even settings where you can apply this sort of
where you can apply this sort of
where you can apply this sort of mathematical reasoning where for example
mathematical reasoning where for example
mathematical reasoning where for example when you're doing mathematical reasoning
when you're doing mathematical reasoning
when you're doing mathematical reasoning about you know um real world systems and
about you know um real world systems and
about you know um real world systems and your the behaviors of these systems have
your the behaviors of these systems have
your the behaviors of these systems have real consequences. So edge cases are
real consequences. So edge cases are
real consequences. So edge cases are really critical. So in these cases you
really critical. So in these cases you
really critical. So in these cases you want your mathematical reasoning to be
want your mathematical reasoning to be
want your mathematical reasoning to be really robust and rigorous. And
really robust and rigorous. And
really robust and rigorous. And unfortunately,
unfortunately,
unfortunately, language-based purely neural
language-based purely neural
language-based purely neural mathematical reasoning tends to not be
mathematical reasoning tends to not be
mathematical reasoning tends to not be this
this
this way. And so, it is entirely possible
way. And so, it is entirely possible
way. And so, it is entirely possible that scaling is going to solve all of
that scaling is going to solve all of
that scaling is going to solve all of these problems, but uh as I said, I'm a
these problems, but uh as I said, I'm a
these problems, but uh as I said, I'm a little bit skeptical about this. So in
little bit skeptical about this. So in
little bit skeptical about this. So in this talk I'm going to
this talk I'm going to
this talk I'm going to demonstrate an alternative strategy
demonstrate an alternative strategy
demonstrate an alternative strategy which is similar in many ways to alpha
which is similar in many ways to alpha
which is similar in many ways to alpha proof which you saw
proof which you saw
proof which you saw previously but which is more of a an LLM
previously but which is more of a an LLM
previously but which is more of a an LLM agent approach that uh is an alternative
agent approach that uh is an alternative
agent approach that uh is an alternative to this sort of purely neural purely
to this sort of purely neural purely
to this sort of purely neural purely language kind of uh model.
So this alternative involves formal
So this alternative involves formal representations uh just like in alpha
representations uh just like in alpha
representations uh just like in alpha proof. So there's an entire literature
proof. So there's an entire literature
proof. So there's an entire literature that is um building up that follows this
that is um building up that follows this
that is um building up that follows this kind of strategy. And so here what you
kind of strategy. And so here what you
kind of strategy. And so here what you do is that rather than just operating in
do is that rather than just operating in
do is that rather than just operating in this space of informal problem
this space of informal problem
this space of informal problem statements and informal solutions, you'd
statements and informal solutions, you'd
statements and informal solutions, you'd be first uh doing what is called auto
be first uh doing what is called auto
be first uh doing what is called auto formalization. So you're going to go
formalization. So you're going to go
formalization. So you're going to go from the informal statement to a formal
from the informal statement to a formal
from the informal statement to a formal statement in a language like lean or
statement in a language like lean or
statement in a language like lean or coaul or isabel and lean in particular
coaul or isabel and lean in particular
coaul or isabel and lean in particular is what is used for alpha proof. uh but
is what is used for alpha proof. uh but
is what is used for alpha proof. uh but uh there are other frameworks like this
uh there are other frameworks like this
uh there are other frameworks like this as well that have a a very long
history. Now the appeal of these sorts
history. Now the appeal of these sorts of formal frameworks is that a proof can
of formal frameworks is that a proof can
of formal frameworks is that a proof can be written in a step-by-step way just
be written in a step-by-step way just
be written in a step-by-step way just like code and not only that a proof can
like code and not only that a proof can
like code and not only that a proof can be checked. You can check if uh if a
be checked. You can check if uh if a
be checked. You can check if uh if a proof uh that you have written in this
proof uh that you have written in this
proof uh that you have written in this formal language actually
formal language actually
formal language actually implies a certain property that you
implies a certain property that you
implies a certain property that you started out with. Uh so this uh theorem
started out with. Uh so this uh theorem
started out with. Uh so this uh theorem that you started out with. And so the
that you started out with. And so the
that you started out with. And so the idea is that you would then in the
idea is that you would then in the
idea is that you would then in the second phase take this formal problem
second phase take this formal problem
second phase take this formal problem statement and then you would be feeding
statement and then you would be feeding
statement and then you would be feeding it to a neural prover which is going to
it to a neural prover which is going to
it to a neural prover which is going to come up with this sequence of steps
come up with this sequence of steps
come up with this sequence of steps which are also called uh tactics. uh
which are also called uh tactics. uh
which are also called uh tactics. uh these these uh rules that you apply. So
these these uh rules that you apply. So
these these uh rules that you apply. So these are um tactics and you apply them
these are um tactics and you apply them
these are um tactics and you apply them one by one and then at the end you get
one by one and then at the end you get
one by one and then at the end you get to uh this uh QED stage uh where you
to uh this uh QED stage uh where you
to uh this uh QED stage uh where you have nothing left to
have nothing left to
have nothing left to prove. And so that that's how uh this
prove. And so that that's how uh this
prove. And so that that's how uh this process would work. And the advantage
process would work. And the advantage
process would work. And the advantage here is that if you think of the
here is that if you think of the
here is that if you think of the verification challenge that I mentioned
verification challenge that I mentioned
verification challenge that I mentioned earlier where you want to check whether
earlier where you want to check whether
earlier where you want to check whether a
a
a claimed proof is actually a proof, this
claimed proof is actually a proof, this
claimed proof is actually a proof, this is something that you can establish uh
is something that you can establish uh
is something that you can establish uh relatively easily using a proof
relatively easily using a proof
relatively easily using a proof assistant, right? Um and in terms of the
assistant, right? Um and in terms of the
assistant, right? Um and in terms of the data issues. So the appeal of this kind
data issues. So the appeal of this kind
data issues. So the appeal of this kind of verifiability is that during training
of verifiability is that during training
of verifiability is that during training time you can synthetically generate a
time you can synthetically generate a
time you can synthetically generate a very very large number of candidate
very very large number of candidate
very very large number of candidate proofs and then you can immediately get
proofs and then you can immediately get
proofs and then you can immediately get feedback or whe on whether or not these
feedback or whe on whether or not these
feedback or whe on whether or not these proofs are correct.
proofs are correct.
proofs are correct. So this turns this difficult problem of
So this turns this difficult problem of
So this turns this difficult problem of proof into this kind of a game playing
proof into this kind of a game playing
proof into this kind of a game playing task uh which you can approach with uh
task uh which you can approach with uh
task uh which you can approach with uh really a version of reinforcement
really a version of reinforcement
really a version of reinforcement learning and this is what for example
learning and this is what for example
learning and this is what for example alpha proof did although I'll show here
alpha proof did although I'll show here
alpha proof did although I'll show here that you can also take a more LLM based
that you can also take a more LLM based
that you can also take a more LLM based approach to this problem and um and uh
approach to this problem and um and uh
approach to this problem and um and uh in fact uh you can build up on these
in fact uh you can build up on these
in fact uh you can build up on these pre-trained language language models and
pre-trained language language models and
pre-trained language language models and only have a pretty thin layer on top of
only have a pretty thin layer on top of
only have a pretty thin layer on top of that and that still does uh quite
that and that still does uh quite
that and that still does uh quite interestingly
interestingly
interestingly well. Okay, so just to go into a little
well. Okay, so just to go into a little
well. Okay, so just to go into a little bit more detail about these formal
bit more detail about these formal
bit more detail about these formal representations even though you may have
representations even though you may have
representations even though you may have seen this in uh the alpha proof lecture
seen this in uh the alpha proof lecture
seen this in uh the alpha proof lecture uh I'll just uh you know quickly recap
uh I'll just uh you know quickly recap
uh I'll just uh you know quickly recap uh recapitulate this. So here is a
uh recapitulate this. So here is a
uh recapitulate this. So here is a theorem that uh we are let's say we are
theorem that uh we are let's say we are
theorem that uh we are let's say we are trying to prove and what this says is
trying to prove and what this says is
trying to prove and what this says is that if x is even then x² is even as
that if x is even then x² is even as
that if x is even then x² is even as well. So the theorem statement over here
well. So the theorem statement over here
well. So the theorem statement over here says that um x is a natural number and
says that um x is a natural number and
says that um x is a natural number and then it says that x um being even uh
then it says that x um being even uh
then it says that x um being even uh implies x² uh is is also even. So modulo
implies x² uh is is also even. So modulo
implies x² uh is is also even. So modulo 2 it's uh the the remainder is zero.
2 it's uh the the remainder is zero.
2 it's uh the the remainder is zero. So now in order to prove this you are
So now in order to prove this you are
So now in order to prove this you are going to uh apply the sequence of
going to uh apply the sequence of
going to uh apply the sequence of tactics as I said previously. Now it's
tactics as I said previously. Now it's
tactics as I said previously. Now it's important to note
important to note
important to note that the system the the the proof
that the system the the the proof
that the system the the the proof assistant it has a certain state that
assistant it has a certain state that
assistant it has a certain state that depends on what the original theorem is
depends on what the original theorem is
depends on what the original theorem is and which tactics you have applied so
and which tactics you have applied so
and which tactics you have applied so far. So for example in the beginning you
far. So for example in the beginning you
far. So for example in the beginning you would have a state that looks like this.
would have a state that looks like this.
would have a state that looks like this. Now just to spell this out what this
Now just to spell this out what this
Now just to spell this out what this means it says that there is one goal
means it says that there is one goal
means it says that there is one goal that you currently need to prove and
that you currently need to prove and
that you currently need to prove and that goal is that under this context
that goal is that under this context
that goal is that under this context which is that x is a natural number uh
which is that x is a natural number uh
which is that x is a natural number uh this is the this is the variable that
this is the this is the variable that
this is the this is the variable that you're allowed to use and then this
you're allowed to use and then this
you're allowed to use and then this symbol turn style means that this is
symbol turn style means that this is
symbol turn style means that this is what you need to prove. So this is
what you need to prove. So this is
what you need to prove. So this is basically the theorem that you're
basically the theorem that you're
basically the theorem that you're starting out with before you have
starting out with before you have
starting out with before you have applied that
applied that
applied that tactic. Now you have the state and then
tactic. Now you have the state and then
tactic. Now you have the state and then you apply the tactic which is you can
you apply the tactic which is you can
you apply the tactic which is you can think of it if you're thinking of this
think of it if you're thinking of this
think of it if you're thinking of this as you know a reinforcement learning
as you know a reinforcement learning
as you know a reinforcement learning setup you are applying an action and so
setup you are applying an action and so
setup you are applying an action and so you apply that action and that leads to
you apply that action and that leads to
you apply that action and that leads to a new state and then this state here
a new state and then this state here
a new state and then this state here looks like this. So this intro tactic
looks like this. So this intro tactic
looks like this. So this intro tactic what it does is that it introduces this
what it does is that it introduces this
what it does is that it introduces this this uh new
this uh new
this uh new hypothesis which over here now says that
hypothesis which over here now says that
hypothesis which over here now says that okay let us assume that x is even along
okay let us assume that x is even along
okay let us assume that x is even along with uh sorry uh yeah x is even along
with uh sorry uh yeah x is even along
with uh sorry uh yeah x is even along with x being a natural number and this
with x being a natural number and this
with x being a natural number and this uh property that x is even we are going
uh property that x is even we are going
uh property that x is even we are going to give it a name h and then under this
to give it a name h and then under this
to give it a name h and then under this context which is really like you know
context which is really like you know
context which is really like you know you have now declared a a new variable
you have now declared a a new variable
you have now declared a a new variable which has a certain uh type attached to
which has a certain uh type attached to
which has a certain uh type attached to to it. Uh so now you are trying to show
to it. Uh so now you are trying to show
to it. Uh so now you are trying to show that this uh x square is even as well
that this uh x square is even as well
that this uh x square is even as well and then you apply this uh next tactic
and then you apply this uh next tactic
and then you apply this uh next tactic which leads to um another state. So
which leads to um another state. So
which leads to um another state. So these tactics are written by humans and
these tactics are written by humans and
these tactics are written by humans and they encode various rules of
they encode various rules of
they encode various rules of simplification in in uh mathematics. And
simplification in in uh mathematics. And
simplification in in uh mathematics. And so what you're really doing is that for
so what you're really doing is that for
so what you're really doing is that for each of these rewrite rules that you're
each of these rewrite rules that you're
each of these rewrite rules that you're applying the state is changing. So for
applying the state is changing. So for
applying the state is changing. So for example now the state has changed to you
example now the state has changed to you
example now the state has changed to you showing that you know if um uh so this
showing that you know if um uh so this
showing that you know if um uh so this um x modulo 2 * x modulo 2 the the whole
um x modulo 2 * x modulo 2 the the whole
um x modulo 2 * x modulo 2 the the whole thing modulo 2 that is equal to zero and
thing modulo 2 that is equal to zero and
thing modulo 2 that is equal to zero and then the next rewrite is going to
then the next rewrite is going to
then the next rewrite is going to simplify this and then finally you will
simplify this and then finally you will
simplify this and then finally you will end up with um you know um 0 equals 0
end up with um you know um 0 equals 0
end up with um you know um 0 equals 0 basically and at that point you're going
basically and at that point you're going
basically and at that point you're going to hit qed because your goal will just
to hit qed because your goal will just
to hit qed because your goal will just disappear right so each of these rules
disappear right so each of these rules
disappear right so each of these rules you can think of as simplifying the
you can think of as simplifying the
you can think of as simplifying the state and then at the end ideally you
state and then at the end ideally you
state and then at the end ideally you want to end up in the state where there
want to end up in the state where there
want to end up in the state where there are no open goals and at that point you
are no open goals and at that point you
are no open goals and at that point you can end the
can end the
can end the proof. So that's what these formal proof
proof. So that's what these formal proof
proof. So that's what these formal proof assistants look like really. They're
assistants look like really. They're
assistants look like really. They're state machines where you have the proof
state machines where you have the proof
state machines where you have the proof state and then these actions which are
state and then these actions which are
state and then these actions which are these tactics and then they lead to a
these tactics and then they lead to a
these tactics and then they lead to a new proof state and and your goal really
new proof state and and your goal really
new proof state and and your goal really is to find a sequence of tactics that
is to find a sequence of tactics that
is to find a sequence of tactics that take you from this initial state of the
take you from this initial state of the
take you from this initial state of the of the of the prover to this qed state
of the of the prover to this qed state
of the of the prover to this qed state where there are no more goals to be
where there are no more goals to be
where there are no more goals to be discharged.
Okay. So now let's uh talk about the two
Okay. So now let's uh talk about the two phases that I mentioned previously. The
phases that I mentioned previously. The
phases that I mentioned previously. The autoformmalization phase is something
autoformmalization phase is something
autoformmalization phase is something like this. You're starting with this
like this. You're starting with this
like this. You're starting with this informal math statement. there exists an
informal math statement. there exists an
informal math statement. there exists an infinite number of primes and then there
infinite number of primes and then there
infinite number of primes and then there is this uh you know um proof of this as
is this uh you know um proof of this as
is this uh you know um proof of this as well in natural language and now you are
well in natural language and now you are
well in natural language and now you are applying your auto formalization model
applying your auto formalization model
applying your auto formalization model and later I'll talk a little bit about
and later I'll talk a little bit about
and later I'll talk a little bit about how this could be done but you know the
how this could be done but you know the
how this could be done but you know the version zero of this would be that you
version zero of this would be that you
version zero of this would be that you throw a language model at this at this
throw a language model at this at this
throw a language model at this at this informal statement and then out comes
informal statement and then out comes
informal statement and then out comes this formal theorem right and and so
this formal theorem right and and so
this formal theorem right and and so this one is in lean uh now what this
this one is in lean uh now what this
this one is in lean uh now what this says uh is that
says uh is that
says uh is that Um well I won't read this uh thing in
Um well I won't read this uh thing in
Um well I won't read this uh thing in detail uh but uh maybe I can read the
detail uh but uh maybe I can read the
detail uh but uh maybe I can read the theorem statement uh it says that so for
theorem statement uh it says that so for
theorem statement uh it says that so for all n there exist a p such that p is
all n there exist a p such that p is
all n there exist a p such that p is bigger than greater than equal to n and
bigger than greater than equal to n and
bigger than greater than equal to n and then p is also a prime right so that's
then p is also a prime right so that's
then p is also a prime right so that's how you establish that there's an
how you establish that there's an
how you establish that there's an infinite number of primes and then the
infinite number of primes and then the
infinite number of primes and then the rest of it is the
proof so then let's assume that you have
proof so then let's assume that you have done this auto formalization. You have a
done this auto formalization. You have a
done this auto formalization. You have a formal statement of a theorem and now
formal statement of a theorem and now
formal statement of a theorem and now you're trying to prove it. So previously
you're trying to prove it. So previously
you're trying to prove it. So previously I showed you that there are these
I showed you that there are these
I showed you that there are these tactics, these simplification rules that
tactics, these simplification rules that
tactics, these simplification rules that you could apply. But now you can imagine
you could apply. But now you can imagine
you could apply. But now you can imagine a search problem where at each state
a search problem where at each state
a search problem where at each state there is a set of
there is a set of
there is a set of potential tactics that you could apply
potential tactics that you could apply
potential tactics that you could apply and this leads to the creation of a
and this leads to the creation of a
and this leads to the creation of a search tree and then your goal is to
search tree and then your goal is to
search tree and then your goal is to basically find a path in this tree that
basically find a path in this tree that
basically find a path in this tree that ends up at QED.
ends up at QED.
ends up at QED. Now of course the complexity over here
Now of course the complexity over here
Now of course the complexity over here is that at each point you can have a
is that at each point you can have a
is that at each point you can have a very very large number of potential
very very large number of potential
very very large number of potential branches in this tree and then also this
branches in this tree and then also this
branches in this tree and then also this tree can be quite deep right because if
tree can be quite deep right because if
tree can be quite deep right because if you're talking about really advanced
you're talking about really advanced
you're talking about really advanced mathematical theorems uh you could um
mathematical theorems uh you could um
mathematical theorems uh you could um end up with proofs that are thousands
end up with proofs that are thousands
end up with proofs that are thousands and thousands of lines long. And so this
and thousands of lines long. And so this
and thousands of lines long. And so this is a far harder problem than any game
is a far harder problem than any game
is a far harder problem than any game playing problem that we have been able
playing problem that we have been able
playing problem that we have been able to solve so far.
to solve so far.
to solve so far. uh so it's remarkable uh to see the kind
uh so it's remarkable uh to see the kind
uh so it's remarkable uh to see the kind of progress uh that has already happened
of progress uh that has already happened
of progress uh that has already happened in this task over the last few
years. Now alpha proof of course you
years. Now alpha proof of course you have already seen uh you've seen this
have already seen uh you've seen this
have already seen uh you've seen this picture there's this formalizer network
picture there's this formalizer network
picture there's this formalizer network that does this formalization into formal
that does this formalization into formal
that does this formalization into formal problems and then the solver network it
problems and then the solver network it
problems and then the solver network it tries to generate these formal proofs.
tries to generate these formal proofs.
tries to generate these formal proofs. Uh one big insight was that even
Uh one big insight was that even
Uh one big insight was that even misformalized problems are still helpful
misformalized problems are still helpful
misformalized problems are still helpful for learning and this sort of proof the
for learning and this sort of proof the
for learning and this sort of proof the solver network this is being trained
solver network this is being trained
solver network this is being trained with RL and then one big insight was
with RL and then one big insight was
with RL and then one big insight was that you could complement RL training
that you could complement RL training
that you could complement RL training with test time RL when you are actually
with test time RL when you are actually
with test time RL when you are actually doing the IMO or any other solving any
doing the IMO or any other solving any
doing the IMO or any other solving any other math problem you are uh you could
other math problem you are uh you could
other math problem you are uh you could generate uh you could basically do this
generate uh you could basically do this
generate uh you could basically do this sort of test time RL um on on that um
sort of test time RL um on on that um
sort of test time RL um on on that um But again you have you've seen all of
But again you have you've seen all of
But again you have you've seen all of this uh so I'll move
this uh so I'll move
this uh so I'll move on the approach that I'm going to talk
on the approach that I'm going to talk
on the approach that I'm going to talk about today this is uh called copra this
about today this is uh called copra this
about today this is uh called copra this was published in a paper um at the
was published in a paper um at the
was published in a paper um at the conference of language models last year
conference of language models last year
conference of language models last year and this is led by my PhD student at UT
and this is led by my PhD student at UT
and this is led by my PhD student at UT Austin Amit
Austin Amit
Austin Amit Takur. Now this is the overall picture
Takur. Now this is the overall picture
Takur. Now this is the overall picture of Copra.
of Copra.
of Copra. it still has this um view of um
it still has this um view of um
it still has this um view of um interaction between uh an LLM that is
interaction between uh an LLM that is
interaction between uh an LLM that is predicting the proof
predicting the proof
predicting the proof steps and um the actual proofer that is
steps and um the actual proofer that is
steps and um the actual proofer that is executing the the step that is proposed
executing the the step that is proposed
executing the the step that is proposed by the LLM and then and then giving you
by the LLM and then and then giving you
by the LLM and then and then giving you a new
a new
a new state. However, the difference is that
state. However, the difference is that
state. However, the difference is that while alpha proof does this sort
while alpha proof does this sort
while alpha proof does this sort of you know uh advanced reinforcement
of you know uh advanced reinforcement
of you know uh advanced reinforcement learning for training. So here you're
learning for training. So here you're
learning for training. So here you're just taking this sort of an LLM agent
just taking this sort of an LLM agent
just taking this sort of an LLM agent approach where uh you have a frontier
approach where uh you have a frontier
approach where uh you have a frontier LLM and the frontier LLM is being
LLM and the frontier LLM is being
LLM and the frontier LLM is being provided the proof state and some
provided the proof state and some
provided the proof state and some information from the history of the
information from the history of the
information from the history of the search so far and then it is making a
search so far and then it is making a
search so far and then it is making a prediction as to what's the next step
prediction as to what's the next step
prediction as to what's the next step step that you should take and then you
step that you should take and then you
step that you should take and then you are taking that step and you're
are taking that step and you're
are taking that step and you're executing it and then you are getting
executing it and then you are getting
executing it and then you are getting back a new state of the of the proof and
back a new state of the of the proof and
back a new state of the of the proof and then this process is continuing right.
then this process is continuing right.
then this process is continuing right. Um now one important thing is that there
Um now one important thing is that there
Um now one important thing is that there is an external search that is going on a
is an external search that is going on a
is an external search that is going on a depth first search and then inside the
depth first search and then inside the
depth first search and then inside the depth first search you are doing all
depth first search you are doing all
depth first search you are doing all this right but it is fundamentally
this right but it is fundamentally
this right but it is fundamentally different in the sense that everything
different in the sense that everything
different in the sense that everything is in context there is um no actual
is in context there is um no actual
is in context there is um no actual adjustment to the way it's happening but
adjustment to the way it's happening but
adjustment to the way it's happening but what is interesting is that even with a
what is interesting is that even with a
what is interesting is that even with a relatively small amount of compute this
relatively small amount of compute this
relatively small amount of compute this approach was still uh able to do quite
approach was still uh able to do quite
approach was still uh able to do quite well and so I think that this strategy
well and so I think that this strategy
well and so I think that this strategy has a lot of long-term promise
has a lot of long-term promise
has a lot of long-term promise for one because it immediately leverages
for one because it immediately leverages
for one because it immediately leverages advances in LLMs as for example you go
advances in LLMs as for example you go
advances in LLMs as for example you go from GPD4 to you know um 01 to 03 and to
from GPD4 to you know um 01 to 03 and to
from GPD4 to you know um 01 to 03 and to you know maybe someday GPD5 then uh
you know maybe someday GPD5 then uh
you know maybe someday GPD5 then uh you're going to immediately leverage
you're going to immediately leverage
you're going to immediately leverage those advantages uh
those advantages uh
those advantages uh advances u and it also has this ability
advances u and it also has this ability
advances u and it also has this ability to integrate natural language and formal
to integrate natural language and formal
to integrate natural language and formal language reasoning uh because ultimately
language reasoning uh because ultimately
language reasoning uh because ultimately you're just using an LLM to generate the
you're just using an LLM to generate the
you're just using an LLM to generate the the proofs in the
the proofs in the
the proofs in the formal formal language but at the same
formal formal language but at the same
formal formal language but at the same time the LLM has the ability to do
time the LLM has the ability to do
time the LLM has the ability to do natural language as well. So this is
natural language as well. So this is
natural language as well. So this is something you can you can benefit from
something you can you can benefit from
something you can you can benefit from and I'm going to show concrete examples
and I'm going to show concrete examples
and I'm going to show concrete examples of this uh in a little
of this uh in a little
of this uh in a little bit. Another thing is that it's also
bit. Another thing is that it's also
bit. Another thing is that it's also this strategy is also applicable even if
this strategy is also applicable even if
this strategy is also applicable even if there is no corpus of training problems.
there is no corpus of training problems.
there is no corpus of training problems. Now, um, one of the challenges in doing
Now, um, one of the challenges in doing
Now, um, one of the challenges in doing AI for math once you go outside of
AI for math once you go outside of
AI for math once you go outside of settings such as math competitions is
settings such as math competitions is
settings such as math competitions is that you're really trying to solve a new
that you're really trying to solve a new
that you're really trying to solve a new problem, right? So, if you're a math
problem, right? So, if you're a math
problem, right? So, if you're a math researcher, you're trying to solve a new
researcher, you're trying to solve a new
researcher, you're trying to solve a new problem that by design is quite
problem that by design is quite
problem that by design is quite different from the problems that a lot
different from the problems that a lot
different from the problems that a lot of other people have solved previously.
of other people have solved previously.
of other people have solved previously. So in such a situation it's a bit
So in such a situation it's a bit
So in such a situation it's a bit challenging to
challenging to
challenging to um create a corpus of training problems
um create a corpus of training problems
um create a corpus of training problems and then and then u do you know training
and then and then u do you know training
and then and then u do you know training of an RL agent. However with an in
of an RL agent. However with an in
of an RL agent. However with an in context learning agent the appeal is
context learning agent the appeal is
context learning agent the appeal is that uh you can still um use it. The LLM
that uh you can still um use it. The LLM
that uh you can still um use it. The LLM has inside it a ton of prior knowledge
has inside it a ton of prior knowledge
has inside it a ton of prior knowledge and that knowledge is something that uh
and that knowledge is something that uh
and that knowledge is something that uh you could benefit from, right? And the
you could benefit from, right? And the
you could benefit from, right? And the LLM can for example bring in knowledge
LLM can for example bring in knowledge
LLM can for example bring in knowledge about related problems uh even though
about related problems uh even though
about related problems uh even though it's not been explicitly trained on them
it's not been explicitly trained on them
it's not been explicitly trained on them uh beyond the pre-training
uh beyond the pre-training
uh beyond the pre-training stage. And in the longer run of course
stage. And in the longer run of course
stage. And in the longer run of course uh the two approaches uh of incontext
uh the two approaches uh of incontext
uh the two approaches uh of incontext learning and and um explicit training
learning and and um explicit training
learning and and um explicit training these are not incompatible. So you could
these are not incompatible. So you could
these are not incompatible. So you could imagine the in context learning agent
imagine the in context learning agent
imagine the in context learning agent being used to generate a lot of
being used to generate a lot of
being used to generate a lot of different traces uh by interaction with
different traces uh by interaction with
different traces uh by interaction with the proof assistant and then you could
the proof assistant and then you could
the proof assistant and then you could use them for uh doing fine-tuning.
use them for uh doing fine-tuning.
use them for uh doing fine-tuning. Now one question that you may have over
Now one question that you may have over
Now one question that you may have over here is that well so do I really need to
here is that well so do I really need to
here is that well so do I really need to even have lean in that case couldn't I
even have lean in that case couldn't I
even have lean in that case couldn't I just rely on you know the LLM alone and
just rely on you know the LLM alone and
just rely on you know the LLM alone and I would say that the difference here is
I would say that the difference here is
I would say that the difference here is that this interaction with the proof
that this interaction with the proof
that this interaction with the proof assistant is still providing you know a
assistant is still providing you know a
assistant is still providing you know a very strong form of grounding. So, for
very strong form of grounding. So, for
very strong form of grounding. So, for example, if you take a step predicted by
example, if you take a step predicted by
example, if you take a step predicted by the LLM and then you find that this is
the LLM and then you find that this is
the LLM and then you find that this is actually an invalid step, you're going
actually an invalid step, you're going
actually an invalid step, you're going to get that feedback right away from the
to get that feedback right away from the
to get that feedback right away from the proof assistant and you can take that
proof assistant and you can take that
proof assistant and you can take that feedback and you can then stick it back
feedback and you can then stick it back
feedback and you can then stick it back into the prompt of the LLM and then you
into the prompt of the LLM and then you
into the prompt of the LLM and then you can um you know uh ask it to continue
can um you know uh ask it to continue
can um you know uh ask it to continue and then hopefully it'll learn from its
and then hopefully it'll learn from its
and then hopefully it'll learn from its mistake and and carry on. Right? So in
mistake and and carry on. Right? So in
mistake and and carry on. Right? So in the long run it's possible that once you
the long run it's possible that once you
the long run it's possible that once you have generated a very very very large
have generated a very very very large
have generated a very very very large number of traces via interaction with
number of traces via interaction with
number of traces via interaction with the prover uh maybe you have fine-tuned
the prover uh maybe you have fine-tuned
the prover uh maybe you have fine-tuned your LLM on this all this data and then
your LLM on this all this data and then
your LLM on this all this data and then the LLM is progressively getting better
the LLM is progressively getting better
the LLM is progressively getting better and better and uh there is a point
and better and uh there is a point
and better and uh there is a point beyond which it just doesn't make any
beyond which it just doesn't make any
beyond which it just doesn't make any mistakes uh with this kind of proof.
mistakes uh with this kind of proof.
mistakes uh with this kind of proof. Maybe we'll get there someday, but we
Maybe we'll get there someday, but we
Maybe we'll get there someday, but we are still pretty far away from uh that
are still pretty far away from uh that
are still pretty far away from uh that possibility. So, at least as of now, I
possibility. So, at least as of now, I
possibility. So, at least as of now, I think that um this sort of interaction
think that um this sort of interaction
think that um this sort of interaction between LLM and proof assistant is still
between LLM and proof assistant is still
between LLM and proof assistant is still extremely
extremely
extremely valuable. Okay, so here is this copra
valuable. Okay, so here is this copra
valuable. Okay, so here is this copra system in a little bit more detail. Uh
system in a little bit more detail. Uh
system in a little bit more detail. Uh so, what is going on here is that you're
so, what is going on here is that you're
so, what is going on here is that you're starting with a formal theorem. Uh but
starting with a formal theorem. Uh but
starting with a formal theorem. Uh but you could also have some informal hints.
you could also have some informal hints.
you could also have some informal hints. You could imagine bringing auto
You could imagine bringing auto
You could imagine bringing auto formalization into this picture as well,
formalization into this picture as well,
formalization into this picture as well, but we didn't. And so the first step is
but we didn't. And so the first step is
but we didn't. And so the first step is that you create a prompt based on the
that you create a prompt based on the
that you create a prompt based on the statement of the
statement of the
statement of the theorem. And then you feed it to an um
theorem. And then you feed it to an um
theorem. And then you feed it to an um an an a frontier LLM and you just uh ask
an an a frontier LLM and you just uh ask
an an a frontier LLM and you just uh ask it to generate some potential tactics uh
it to generate some potential tactics uh
it to generate some potential tactics uh that would be of interest. And now you
that would be of interest. And now you
that would be of interest. And now you um you do the uh you your model has has
um you do the uh you your model has has
um you do the uh you your model has has predicted you know a set of one of the
predicted you know a set of one of the
predicted you know a set of one of the actions uh or or tactics in this case
actions uh or or tactics in this case
actions uh or or tactics in this case and then you parse that tactic uh
and then you parse that tactic uh
and then you parse that tactic uh because it'll be in the form of text. So
because it'll be in the form of text. So
because it'll be in the form of text. So now you parse it into a structured
now you parse it into a structured
now you parse it into a structured format and then you just execute it via
format and then you just execute it via
format and then you just execute it via uh the proof environment the and this
uh the proof environment the and this
uh the proof environment the and this could be lean or or coaul orl and then
could be lean or or coaul orl and then
could be lean or or coaul orl and then after you do that uh in the lucky case
after you do that uh in the lucky case
after you do that uh in the lucky case you already hit qed and this is all
you already hit qed and this is all
you already hit qed and this is all done. But uh if you fail, if this uh
done. But uh if you fail, if this uh
done. But uh if you fail, if this uh tactic is is invalid or there are still
tactic is is invalid or there are still
tactic is is invalid or there are still some um some open goals that you still
some um some open goals that you still
some um some open goals that you still need to resolve, in that case you uh get
need to resolve, in that case you uh get
need to resolve, in that case you uh get some feedback and then you you know
some feedback and then you you know
some feedback and then you you know augment the prompt um and then backtrack
augment the prompt um and then backtrack
augment the prompt um and then backtrack if needed and then you uh we also have
if needed and then you uh we also have
if needed and then you uh we also have this retrieval phase over here um which
this retrieval phase over here um which
this retrieval phase over here um which seem to add to the performance. of the
seem to add to the performance. of the
seem to add to the performance. of the system. Uh and uh here you are also able
system. Uh and uh here you are also able
system. Uh and uh here you are also able to query a lema database and bring in
to query a lema database and bring in
to query a lema database and bring in some relevant lemmas and then add it
some relevant lemmas and then add it
some relevant lemmas and then add it back to the prompt. And this process
back to the prompt. And this process
back to the prompt. And this process just continues over and over and over
just continues over and over and over
just continues over and over and over again until you have uh resolved the
again until you have uh resolved the
again until you have uh resolved the original theorem or alternatively you
original theorem or alternatively you
original theorem or alternatively you have timed
have timed
have timed out. So here's the prompt of the system
out. So here's the prompt of the system
out. So here's the prompt of the system in a little bit more detail. So here as
in a little bit more detail. So here as
in a little bit more detail. So here as you see there is the serialized proof
you see there is the serialized proof
you see there is the serialized proof state and uh here you have you know what
state and uh here you have you know what
state and uh here you have you know what is the goal that you still have to prove
is the goal that you still have to prove
is the goal that you still have to prove and what are the hypothesis that uh that
and what are the hypothesis that uh that
and what are the hypothesis that uh that are being made. So over here for example
are being made. So over here for example
are being made. So over here for example the hypothesis include uh these are the
the hypothesis include uh these are the
the hypothesis include uh these are the assumptions you're making right so this
assumptions you're making right so this
assumptions you're making right so this includes x being of type n natural
includes x being of type n natural
includes x being of type n natural numbers and then also you know x being
numbers and then also you know x being
numbers and then also you know x being even um and then you have the goal which
even um and then you have the goal which
even um and then you have the goal which is x² modulo 2 is equal to zero
is x² modulo 2 is equal to zero
is x² modulo 2 is equal to zero uh we also have this information about
uh we also have this information about
uh we also have this information about the last step so the way to read this is
the last step so the way to read this is
the last step so the way to read this is that from left to right you are looking
that from left to right you are looking
that from left to right you are looking at successive queries to the LLM so the
at successive queries to the LLM so the
at successive queries to the LLM so the the first column over here this includes
the first column over here this includes
the first column over here this includes information about you know what is the
information about you know what is the
information about you know what is the first query that you're making. So the
first query that you're making. So the
first query that you're making. So the first thing that you have done so let's
first thing that you have done so let's
first thing that you have done so let's say that you you already have uh made
say that you you already have uh made
say that you you already have uh made this um uh decision that you're going to
this um uh decision that you're going to
this um uh decision that you're going to have this intro tactic right so that's
have this intro tactic right so that's
have this intro tactic right so that's what created that hypothesis x² modulo 2
what created that hypothesis x² modulo 2
what created that hypothesis x² modulo 2 equals z so then this is the last step
equals z so then this is the last step
equals z so then this is the last step this is stored in a stack and and uh fed
this is stored in a stack and and uh fed
this is stored in a stack and and uh fed as part of the prompt
as part of the prompt
as part of the prompt um now uh then uh at this point there
um now uh then uh at this point there
um now uh then uh at this point there has been no error uh so Then you know
has been no error uh so Then you know
has been no error uh so Then you know you um get this response from this LLM.
you um get this response from this LLM.
you um get this response from this LLM. uh after you feed this information that
uh after you feed this information that
uh after you feed this information that the next thing that you should do is
the next thing that you should do is
the next thing that you should do is rw and then uh now if you try to execute
rw and then uh now if you try to execute
rw and then uh now if you try to execute it you might get you know an error
it you might get you know an error
it you might get you know an error message uh because a rewrite tactic
message uh because a rewrite tactic
message uh because a rewrite tactic failed and then u you know this
failed and then u you know this
failed and then u you know this information this this error feedback you
information this this error feedback you
information this this error feedback you send it back to the LLM and then that's
send it back to the LLM and then that's
send it back to the LLM and then that's the next query you say that try again
the next query you say that try again
the next query you say that try again LLM and then the LLM says that okay
LLM and then the LLM says that okay
LLM and then the LLM says that okay let's try apply nack.m mullm mod Right?
let's try apply nack.m mullm mod Right?
let's try apply nack.m mullm mod Right? Uh now the details of this tactic
Uh now the details of this tactic
Uh now the details of this tactic doesn't matter. It's you know something
doesn't matter. It's you know something
doesn't matter. It's you know something involving modular multiplication but the
involving modular multiplication but the
involving modular multiplication but the point is this is also wrong. So then
point is this is also wrong. So then
point is this is also wrong. So then again at the next step you get an error
again at the next step you get an error
again at the next step you get an error feedback error message and this is
feedback error message and this is
feedback error message and this is something you stick back into the prompt
something you stick back into the prompt
something you stick back into the prompt and then you make a query again and now
and then you make a query again and now
and then you make a query again and now it says oh let's try this uh rewrite
it says oh let's try this uh rewrite
it says oh let's try this uh rewrite with
with
with nat.mullmod and yay this time it works.
nat.mullmod and yay this time it works.
nat.mullmod and yay this time it works. So now you see that the interaction
So now you see that the interaction
So now you see that the interaction result doesn't have any error message in
result doesn't have any error message in
result doesn't have any error message in it. It's a success and so um so this is
it. It's a success and so um so this is
it. It's a success and so um so this is now put into the stack and so the last
now put into the stack and so the last
now put into the stack and so the last step as you see has changed. It's now
RWN.mmod. So now you're going to make
RWN.mmod. So now you're going to make the try to generate the next step and
the try to generate the next step and
the try to generate the next step and then this time it the llm generates this
then this time it the llm generates this
then this time it the llm generates this uh uh rw right and so this is how this
uh uh rw right and so this is how this
uh uh rw right and so this is how this process is going to continue in a
process is going to continue in a
process is going to continue in a nutshell. you may query the LLM, get a
nutshell. you may query the LLM, get a
nutshell. you may query the LLM, get a uh an some error error message and then
uh an some error error message and then
uh an some error error message and then stick it back into the prompt and then
stick it back into the prompt and then
stick it back into the prompt and then continue, right? And and this process
continue, right? And and this process
continue, right? And and this process would just um go
would just um go
would just um go on. Okay, so this um evaluation was done
on. Okay, so this um evaluation was done
on. Okay, so this um evaluation was done in 2024 actually late 2023. So you know
in 2024 actually late 2023. So you know
in 2024 actually late 2023. So you know the world has changed since then but at
the world has changed since then but at
the world has changed since then but at least at that point we compared with
least at that point we compared with
least at that point we compared with GPT4 and found that GPT4 frequently gave
GPT4 and found that GPT4 frequently gave
GPT4 and found that GPT4 frequently gave incorrect errors uh incorrect uh proofs
incorrect errors uh incorrect uh proofs
incorrect errors uh incorrect uh proofs um and uh by contrast this feedback with
um and uh by contrast this feedback with
um and uh by contrast this feedback with um with uh the proof environment uh lean
um with uh the proof environment uh lean
um with uh the proof environment uh lean in this case really helped po Copra and
in this case really helped po Copra and
in this case really helped po Copra and so even though it was using the same
so even though it was using the same
so even though it was using the same underlying model the interaction allowed
underlying model the interaction allowed
underlying model the interaction allowed it to create a correct proof uh in this
case. Here are some experimental
case. Here are some experimental results. You can see the details in in
results. You can see the details in in
results. You can see the details in in uh the paper. But uh in this picture on
uh the paper. But uh in this picture on
uh the paper. But uh in this picture on the x-axis you see the number of queries
the x-axis you see the number of queries
the x-axis you see the number of queries and on the y-axis you see the number of
and on the y-axis you see the number of
and on the y-axis you see the number of theorems proved. So what we saw over
theorems proved. So what we saw over
theorems proved. So what we saw over here is that uh pretty quickly the copra
here is that uh pretty quickly the copra
here is that uh pretty quickly the copra approach was able to prove a lot of
approach was able to prove a lot of
approach was able to prove a lot of theorems uh with a relatively small
theorems uh with a relatively small
theorems uh with a relatively small number of queries. uh whereas um the
number of queries. uh whereas um the
number of queries. uh whereas um the other approaches that um that didn't get
other approaches that um that didn't get
other approaches that um that didn't get that uh
far and here is an evaluation on mini
far and here is an evaluation on mini F2F test. So the absolute numbers are
F2F test. So the absolute numbers are
F2F test. So the absolute numbers are not great but then you know the amount
not great but then you know the amount
not great but then you know the amount of compute we provided copra was also
of compute we provided copra was also
of compute we provided copra was also relatively small. Uh we just allowed you
relatively small. Uh we just allowed you
relatively small. Uh we just allowed you know 60 queries uh per proof attempt.
know 60 queries uh per proof attempt.
know 60 queries uh per proof attempt. Now
Now
Now um what we saw here was that we got uh
um what we saw here was that we got uh
um what we saw here was that we got uh you know quite reasonable performance uh
you know quite reasonable performance uh
you know quite reasonable performance uh comparable with the state-of-the-art uh
comparable with the state-of-the-art uh
comparable with the state-of-the-art uh methods. Now um of course since then the
methods. Now um of course since then the
methods. Now um of course since then the state-of-the-art on this benchmark has
state-of-the-art on this benchmark has
state-of-the-art on this benchmark has moved quite a bit. So mini F2F for those
moved quite a bit. So mini F2F for those
moved quite a bit. So mini F2F for those of you who don't know is by the way it's
of you who don't know is by the way it's
of you who don't know is by the way it's a compilation of competition mathematics
a compilation of competition mathematics
a compilation of competition mathematics problems um mostly at the high school
problems um mostly at the high school
problems um mostly at the high school level.
level.
level. and uh so the so it's of the form that
and uh so the so it's of the form that
and uh so the so it's of the form that here is a theorem and come up with a
here is a theorem and come up with a
here is a theorem and come up with a lean proof. So here what we see is that
lean proof. So here what we see is that
lean proof. So here what we see is that there was this um around 29% or or 30%
there was this um around 29% or or 30%
there was this um around 29% or or 30% uh success rate uh which was is uh
uh success rate uh which was is uh
uh success rate uh which was is uh behind the current sort but I think one
behind the current sort but I think one
behind the current sort but I think one question would be that if you take this
question would be that if you take this
question would be that if you take this approach and scale it up then where
approach and scale it up then where
approach and scale it up then where would you end up uh and uh there are no
would you end up uh and uh there are no
would you end up uh and uh there are no public results on that yet.
So in this talk though I'm going
So in this talk though I'm going to go beyond the method that we just
to go beyond the method that we just
to go beyond the method that we just presented which is the basic copra and
presented which is the basic copra and
presented which is the basic copra and um talk about some results that we are
um talk about some results that we are
um talk about some results that we are uh we just recently developed. This is
uh we just recently developed. This is
uh we just recently developed. This is not uh published yet. And here we
not uh published yet. And here we
not uh published yet. And here we are leveraging the ability of LLMs to
are leveraging the ability of LLMs to
are leveraging the ability of LLMs to abstract and also to uh use natural
abstract and also to uh use natural
abstract and also to uh use natural language reasoning. Uh because I think
language reasoning. Uh because I think
language reasoning. Uh because I think that this is really where the sort of
that this is really where the sort of
that this is really where the sort of approach that that we just presented.
approach that that we just presented.
approach that that we just presented. This shines because of the tremendous
This shines because of the tremendous
This shines because of the tremendous amount of world knowledge that is stored
amount of world knowledge that is stored
amount of world knowledge that is stored inside LLMs. uh we can we can really use
inside LLMs. uh we can we can really use
inside LLMs. uh we can we can really use them in a lot more powerful capacity
them in a lot more powerful capacity
them in a lot more powerful capacity than just as a predictor of the next
than just as a predictor of the next
than just as a predictor of the next tactic. And so here's a simple a sample
tactic. And so here's a simple a sample
tactic. And so here's a simple a sample problem. Uh this is from IMO and this is
problem. Uh this is from IMO and this is
problem. Uh this is from IMO and this is saying that you know prove that the this
saying that you know prove that the this
saying that you know prove that the this fraction is irreducible for every
fraction is irreducible for every
fraction is irreducible for every natural number
natural number
natural number n. So what we'll see is that the copra
n. So what we'll see is that the copra
n. So what we'll see is that the copra approach can be extended a little bit to
approach can be extended a little bit to
approach can be extended a little bit to um in fact come up with a hierarchical
um in fact come up with a hierarchical
um in fact come up with a hierarchical solution to this
solution to this
solution to this problem. And so uh this will involve
problem. And so uh this will involve
problem. And so uh this will involve breaking down the problem into sub
breaking down the problem into sub
breaking down the problem into sub problems and then solving
problems and then solving
problems and then solving hierarchically. Okay. So how do we do
hierarchically. Okay. So how do we do
hierarchically. Okay. So how do we do this? Well, first what we do is that we
this? Well, first what we do is that we
this? Well, first what we do is that we ask the LLM to come up with an informal
ask the LLM to come up with an informal
ask the LLM to come up with an informal solution to this
solution to this
solution to this problem. And uh so I don't know if this
problem. And uh so I don't know if this
problem. And uh so I don't know if this uh font is too small to read but
uh font is too small to read but
uh font is too small to read but basically what is going on here is that
basically what is going on here is that
basically what is going on here is that uh this was fed to 03 a reasoning model
uh this was fed to 03 a reasoning model
uh this was fed to 03 a reasoning model and so it was able to come up with this
and so it was able to come up with this
and so it was able to come up with this you know step-by-step plan. Um so for
you know step-by-step plan. Um so for
you know step-by-step plan. Um so for example uh you first define the GCD and
example uh you first define the GCD and
example uh you first define the GCD and then you you know um subtract to
then you you know um subtract to
then you you know um subtract to simplify then you apply the uklidian
simplify then you apply the uklidian
simplify then you apply the uklidian algorithm and then you conclude
algorithm and then you conclude
algorithm and then you conclude something about the GCD and then you
something about the GCD and then you
something about the GCD and then you have the final
have the final
have the final conclusion. So then we say that okay so
conclusion. So then we say that okay so
conclusion. So then we say that okay so let's take this informal
let's take this informal
let's take this informal decomposition and put it in the context.
decomposition and put it in the context.
decomposition and put it in the context. Now let's say that um it's our goal to
Now let's say that um it's our goal to
Now let's say that um it's our goal to prove this lema in lean 4 right so this
prove this lema in lean 4 right so this
prove this lema in lean 4 right so this is the formal statement of the same
is the formal statement of the same
is the formal statement of the same problem and we are just saying that
problem and we are just saying that
problem and we are just saying that don't try to write the proof okay so
don't try to write the proof okay so
don't try to write the proof okay so let's just write the sub goals that are
let's just write the sub goals that are
let's just write the sub goals that are needed to prove this uh but uh we are
needed to prove this uh but uh we are
needed to prove this uh but uh we are doing this conditioned on the informal
doing this conditioned on the informal
doing this conditioned on the informal proof that we just uh
proof that we just uh
proof that we just uh generated and so here is the the proof
generated and so here is the the proof
generated and so here is the the proof of uh or or here is the decomposition of
of uh or or here is the decomposition of
of uh or or here is the decomposition of this lema. So what you see is that um it
this lema. So what you see is that um it
this lema. So what you see is that um it comes up with you know these uh these uh
comes up with you know these uh these uh
comes up with you know these uh these uh three sub goals. So first you uh show
three sub goals. So first you uh show
three sub goals. So first you uh show that um you know uh this this GCD step
that um you know uh this this GCD step
that um you know uh this this GCD step one is true. Um, and it's basically
one is true. Um, and it's basically
one is true. Um, and it's basically saying that this GCD of 21 n + 4 * 14 n
saying that this GCD of 21 n + 4 * 14 n
saying that this GCD of 21 n + 4 * 14 n + 3 is the same as the gcd of this, you
+ 3 is the same as the gcd of this, you
+ 3 is the same as the gcd of this, you know, 14 n + 3 uh * 7 n +
1. So then the there is the second one
1. So then the there is the second one then there's the third one and um and
then there's the third one and um and
then there's the third one and um and and uh so on and so forth and then
and uh so on and so forth and then
and uh so on and so forth and then finally you have the main theorem that
finally you have the main theorem that
finally you have the main theorem that combines all of the above.
combines all of the above.
combines all of the above. So the appeal of this sort of
So the appeal of this sort of
So the appeal of this sort of decomposition is
decomposition is
decomposition is [Applause]
[Applause]
[Applause] that now this very complex problem has
that now this very complex problem has
that now this very complex problem has been simplified into these three sub
been simplified into these three sub
been simplified into these three sub problems which are a lot more tractable.
problems which are a lot more tractable.
problems which are a lot more tractable. So then then in the next step we then
So then then in the next step we then
So then then in the next step we then ask uh copra to solve the sub problems
ask uh copra to solve the sub problems
ask uh copra to solve the sub problems one by one and what we see is that uh
one by one and what we see is that uh
one by one and what we see is that uh copra is in fact able to come up with
copra is in fact able to come up with
copra is in fact able to come up with these uh these proofs of the sub
these uh these proofs of the sub
these uh these proofs of the sub problems and here we are here are the
problems and here we are here are the
problems and here we are here are the proofs again I'm not going to go into
proofs again I'm not going to go into
proofs again I'm not going to go into the details of the proofs this is
the details of the proofs this is
the details of the proofs this is something that uh you know you have to
something that uh you know you have to
something that uh you know you have to stare at for a little bit and and it's
stare at for a little bit and and it's
stare at for a little bit and and it's not actually especially
not actually especially
not actually especially complicated. But then once you have
complicated. But then once you have
complicated. But then once you have proven these um these lemas then you
proven these um these lemas then you
proven these um these lemas then you just put them all in the context and
just put them all in the context and
just put them all in the context and then you also put in the informal proof
then you also put in the informal proof
then you also put in the informal proof and then you ask Copra to prove the the
and then you ask Copra to prove the the
and then you ask Copra to prove the the full
full
full theorem and it is able to do
theorem and it is able to do
theorem and it is able to do that but Copra is not able to prove
that but Copra is not able to prove
that but Copra is not able to prove this. if you were giving it just this um
this. if you were giving it just this um
this. if you were giving it just this um this entire theorem all in all as one
this entire theorem all in all as one
this entire theorem all in all as one block and just asked it to
block and just asked it to
block and just asked it to solve. So what we did here is really you
solve. So what we did here is really you
solve. So what we did here is really you know something that is a a a highly
know something that is a a a highly
know something that is a a a highly powerful design pattern in in uh LLM
powerful design pattern in in uh LLM
powerful design pattern in in uh LLM agents. LLM agents are extraordinarily
agents. LLM agents are extraordinarily
agents. LLM agents are extraordinarily flexible.
flexible.
flexible. So with just some variations on the ways
So with just some variations on the ways
So with just some variations on the ways you do prompting, you were able to make
you do prompting, you were able to make
you do prompting, you were able to make it do very very different things, things
it do very very different things, things
it do very very different things, things that would take a tremendous amount of
that would take a tremendous amount of
that would take a tremendous amount of training if you weren't using these
training if you weren't using these
training if you weren't using these pre-trained models.
pre-trained models.
pre-trained models. And uh so what we did over here is that
And uh so what we did over here is that
And uh so what we did over here is that we started with a system that was just
we started with a system that was just
we started with a system that was just designed to be a step-by-step predictor
designed to be a step-by-step predictor
designed to be a step-by-step predictor of a low-level proof and then we made it
of a low-level proof and then we made it
of a low-level proof and then we made it do highle reasoning at this more
do highle reasoning at this more
do highle reasoning at this more abstract level right because if you can
abstract level right because if you can
abstract level right because if you can think of you can think of these um sub
think of you can think of these um sub
think of you can think of these um sub goals as basically being abstractions of
goals as basically being abstractions of
goals as basically being abstractions of the of of sub problems and so the LLM is
the of of sub problems and so the LLM is
the of of sub problems and so the LLM is able to create these abstractions
able to create these abstractions
able to create these abstractions Right? And once you have created made
Right? And once you have created made
Right? And once you have created made use of these
use of these
use of these abstractions, your uh proof process
abstractions, your uh proof process
abstractions, your uh proof process becomes a lot simpler because now you're
becomes a lot simpler because now you're
becomes a lot simpler because now you're able to go
able to go
able to go hierarchically. And all of this was
hierarchically. And all of this was
hierarchically. And all of this was doable without any substantial training.
doable without any substantial training.
doable without any substantial training. You were just using the power of
You were just using the power of
You were just using the power of prompting. Right? And to me, this is a
prompting. Right? And to me, this is a
prompting. Right? And to me, this is a huge revelation. the idea that you can
huge revelation. the idea that you can
huge revelation. the idea that you can use the power of language, the power of
use the power of language, the power of
use the power of language, the power of all of the stored knowledge you inside
all of the stored knowledge you inside
all of the stored knowledge you inside LLMs and then combine that with the sort
LLMs and then combine that with the sort
LLMs and then combine that with the sort of you know higher level algorithmics
of you know higher level algorithmics
of you know higher level algorithmics where you just you know put together the
where you just you know put together the
where you just you know put together the informal and formal reasoning steps in
informal and formal reasoning steps in
informal and formal reasoning steps in various ways um and change the prompting
various ways um and change the prompting
various ways um and change the prompting strategy and you get something you know
strategy and you get something you know
strategy and you get something you know uh that is qualitatively different in in
uh that is qualitatively different in in
uh that is qualitatively different in in capability.
Um and now it turns out that uh the lean
Um and now it turns out that uh the lean feedback here was also really important
feedback here was also really important
feedback here was also really important uh because at least with 03 mini what we
uh because at least with 03 mini what we
uh because at least with 03 mini what we found is that there were hallucinated
found is that there were hallucinated
found is that there were hallucinated lemas and so on and the grounding that
lemas and so on and the grounding that
lemas and so on and the grounding that was provided by the lean theorem prover
was provided by the lean theorem prover
was provided by the lean theorem prover was absolutely critical um to solve this
problem. So now I want to uh talk a
problem. So now I want to uh talk a little bit about a different application
little bit about a different application
little bit about a different application of the same idea. This is in the context
of the same idea. This is in the context
of the same idea. This is in the context of formal system verification which is
of formal system verification which is
of formal system verification which is one of the most practical applications
one of the most practical applications
one of the most practical applications of rigorous mathematical
of rigorous mathematical
of rigorous mathematical reasoning. And so what you're doing in
reasoning. And so what you're doing in
reasoning. And so what you're doing in formal verification is that you're
formal verification is that you're
formal verification is that you're mathematically modeling a real world
mathematically modeling a real world
mathematically modeling a real world system as a set of
system as a set of
system as a set of definitions and then you are modeling
definitions and then you are modeling
definitions and then you are modeling system properties as theorems involving
system properties as theorems involving
system properties as theorems involving these definitions and then you're
these definitions and then you're
these definitions and then you're proving these
proving these
proving these theorems. These methods have led to
theorems. These methods have led to
theorems. These methods have led to extremely rigorous systems. Systems that
extremely rigorous systems. Systems that
extremely rigorous systems. Systems that are very difficult to or or almost
are very difficult to or or almost
are very difficult to or or almost impossible to hack. For example, there
impossible to hack. For example, there
impossible to hack. For example, there was this time in a program organized by
was this time in a program organized by
was this time in a program organized by the US Department of
Defense. They used this uh formally
Defense. They used this uh formally verified Linux kernel called
verified Linux kernel called
verified Linux kernel called 4 to um and and they put this on a drone
4 to um and and they put this on a drone
4 to um and and they put this on a drone and then they got a red team to try to
and then they got a red team to try to
and then they got a red team to try to attack this drone for a period of six
attack this drone for a period of six
attack this drone for a period of six weeks and they failed right because the
weeks and they failed right because the
weeks and they failed right because the rigor provided by formal verification
rigor provided by formal verification
rigor provided by formal verification was just so
was just so
was just so much. Now historically formal
much. Now historically formal
much. Now historically formal verification has been extremely
verification has been extremely
verification has been extremely expensive and as a result its costs
expensive and as a result its costs
expensive and as a result its costs uh it's not really been widely deployed
uh it's not really been widely deployed
uh it's not really been widely deployed because the costs are not justifiable
because the costs are not justifiable
because the costs are not justifiable except in the most safety critical
except in the most safety critical
except in the most safety critical scenarios. However, with the rise of AI,
scenarios. However, with the rise of AI,
scenarios. However, with the rise of AI, especially AI for math, the costbenefit
especially AI for math, the costbenefit
especially AI for math, the costbenefit equation changes quite
equation changes quite
equation changes quite drastically and uh now um you can
drastically and uh now um you can
drastically and uh now um you can imagine you know doing not only proofs
imagine you know doing not only proofs
imagine you know doing not only proofs of math but proofs of real world systems
of math but proofs of real world systems
of math but proofs of real world systems uh of for example correctness, security,
uh of for example correctness, security,
uh of for example correctness, security, performance and so on uh using this
performance and so on uh using this
performance and so on uh using this growing generation of AI tools.
growing generation of AI tools.
growing generation of AI tools. So here I'm going to show you a basic
So here I'm going to show you a basic
So here I'm going to show you a basic example of this idea. Uh this can be
example of this idea. Uh this can be
example of this idea. Uh this can be scaled up substantially with um uh with
scaled up substantially with um uh with
scaled up substantially with um uh with more powerful models and more
more powerful models and more
more powerful models and more compute. But uh here what we are going
compute. But uh here what we are going
compute. But uh here what we are going to do is to give you a very very basic
to do is to give you a very very basic
to do is to give you a very very basic compiler and then show how to formally
compiler and then show how to formally
compiler and then show how to formally verify its correctness.
verify its correctness.
verify its correctness. Now this is so simple the compiler that
Now this is so simple the compiler that
Now this is so simple the compiler that it's almost a joke but um trust me when
it's almost a joke but um trust me when
it's almost a joke but um trust me when you go to more advanced compiler design
you go to more advanced compiler design
you go to more advanced compiler design the fundamentals don't change it's
the fundamentals don't change it's
the fundamentals don't change it's really the same sort of idea it's just
really the same sort of idea it's just
really the same sort of idea it's just that there are there is more
that there are there is more
that there are there is more complexity now okay to um do compiler
complexity now okay to um do compiler
complexity now okay to um do compiler verification you would need the
verification you would need the
verification you would need the following pieces so first of all you
following pieces so first of all you
following pieces so first of all you would need to have a notion of um
would need to have a notion of um
would need to have a notion of um language and a language consists of a
language and a language consists of a
language and a language consists of a syntax and a semantics. So syntax is a
syntax and a semantics. So syntax is a
syntax and a semantics. So syntax is a grammar that defines the form of the
grammar that defines the form of the
grammar that defines the form of the programs and then semantics are the
programs and then semantics are the
programs and then semantics are the rules that define the executions of
rules that define the executions of
rules that define the executions of programs and then a compiler is
programs and then a compiler is
programs and then a compiler is basically a set of rules that translate
basically a set of rules that translate
basically a set of rules that translate programs from one language to another
programs from one language to another
programs from one language to another and then verifications is that you you
and then verifications is that you you
and then verifications is that you you prove that the rules preserve
semantics. So here we are going to talk
semantics. So here we are going to talk about a very basic expression language
about a very basic expression language
about a very basic expression language in which you are allowed to do addition
in which you are allowed to do addition
in which you are allowed to do addition and multiplication. So this is just
and multiplication. So this is just
and multiplication. So this is just basic arithmetic expressions and this
basic arithmetic expressions and this
basic arithmetic expressions and this syntax that you see over here this is in
syntax that you see over here this is in
syntax that you see over here this is in a language called coaul and
a language called coaul and
a language called coaul and um here it's it looks a lot like lean
um here it's it looks a lot like lean
um here it's it looks a lot like lean it's a similar you know uh dependently
it's a similar you know uh dependently
it's a similar you know uh dependently typed functional programming language
typed functional programming language
typed functional programming language and so what you're doing over here is
and so what you're doing over here is
and so what you're doing over here is that you're defining this binary
that you're defining this binary
that you're defining this binary operator this can be either plus or
operator this can be either plus or
operator this can be either plus or times you're defining this notion of an
times you're defining this notion of an
times you're defining this notion of an expression and uh this is saying that it
expression and uh this is saying that it
expression and uh this is saying that it can be either a constant or a binary
can be either a constant or a binary
can be either a constant or a binary operation. Um and then there is uh there
operation. Um and then there is uh there
operation. Um and then there is uh there are some rules that tell you you know
are some rules that tell you you know
are some rules that tell you you know how to
how to
how to actually evaluate the uh these
actually evaluate the uh these
actually evaluate the uh these expressions you know uh if you if you're
expressions you know uh if you if you're
expressions you know uh if you if you're given an expression what will be the
given an expression what will be the
given an expression what will be the result when you evaluate it and I'm not
result when you evaluate it and I'm not
result when you evaluate it and I'm not going to go into the rules in detail
going to go into the rules in detail
going to go into the rules in detail I'll share the slides and if you're
I'll share the slides and if you're
I'll share the slides and if you're interested you can uh
interested you can uh
interested you can uh um well you can look up many resources
um well you can look up many resources
um well you can look up many resources on the on the web but also I'm happy to
on the on the web but also I'm happy to
on the on the web but also I'm happy to answer questions over
offline or actually after this talk.
offline or actually after this talk. Okay. So then you define the source
Okay. So then you define the source
Okay. So then you define the source language. So here what you see is that
language. So here what you see is that
language. So here what you see is that you can define you know the the rules
you can define you know the the rules
you can define you know the the rules that we saw previously they allow you to
that we saw previously they allow you to
that we saw previously they allow you to define the semantics of quite complex
define the semantics of quite complex
define the semantics of quite complex expressions. So here what you're seeing
expressions. So here what you're seeing
expressions. So here what you're seeing is that you know you have const 2. So uh
is that you know you have const 2. So uh
is that you know you have const 2. So uh an an expression can be a constant or a
an an expression can be a constant or a
an an expression can be a constant or a binary operation or the result of a
binary operation or the result of a
binary operation or the result of a binary operation. And you see that you
binary operation. And you see that you
binary operation. And you see that you know this is the result of applying a
know this is the result of applying a
know this is the result of applying a binary operation to two expressions you
binary operation to two expressions you
binary operation to two expressions you know and so this is a recursive
know and so this is a recursive
know and so this is a recursive definition really and then you are um
definition really and then you are um
definition really and then you are um getting an expression as as output. Uh
getting an expression as as output. Uh
getting an expression as as output. Uh so here what you're seeing is that you
so here what you're seeing is that you
so here what you're seeing is that you are um you can evaluate various
are um you can evaluate various
are um you can evaluate various complicated expressions in this
complicated expressions in this
complicated expressions in this way. And so now you have to define the
way. And so now you have to define the
way. And so now you have to define the target language right? So this is the a
target language right? So this is the a
target language right? So this is the a compiler is a mapping from a source
compiler is a mapping from a source
compiler is a mapping from a source language to a target language. So now
language to a target language. So now
language to a target language. So now you have to define the target language
you have to define the target language
you have to define the target language and so what you did over here is that uh
and so what you did over here is that uh
and so what you did over here is that uh you are defining the target language as
you are defining the target language as
you are defining the target language as a list of instructions. So a program is
a list of instructions. So a program is
a list of instructions. So a program is a list of instructions and an
a list of instructions and an
a list of instructions and an instruction is either this sort of a
instruction is either this sort of a
instruction is either this sort of a constant expression or a binary
constant expression or a binary
constant expression or a binary operation expression. So one way to see
operation expression. So one way to see
operation expression. So one way to see it is that while the original expression
it is that while the original expression
it is that while the original expression in the in the source language was
in the in the source language was
in the in the source language was defined in this recursive way in
defined in this recursive way in
defined in this recursive way in the in the um target language when you
the in the um target language when you
the in the um target language when you are interpreting it you are doing it
are interpreting it you are doing it
are interpreting it you are doing it using a stack. So this is a well-known
using a stack. So this is a well-known
using a stack. So this is a well-known idea in programming languages that if
idea in programming languages that if
idea in programming languages that if you have a
you have a
you have a recursive expression you know let's say
recursive expression you know let's say
recursive expression you know let's say an arithmetic expression then the way
an arithmetic expression then the way
an arithmetic expression then the way you can execute it is by maintaining a
you can execute it is by maintaining a
you can execute it is by maintaining a stack and you can you know keep pushing
stack and you can you know keep pushing
stack and you can you know keep pushing the current instruction on the stack and
the current instruction on the stack and
the current instruction on the stack and you can basically uh do this kind of a
you can basically uh do this kind of a
you can basically uh do this kind of a low-level you know build up a low-level
low-level you know build up a low-level
low-level you know build up a low-level machine a stack machine uh actually a
machine a stack machine uh actually a
machine a stack machine uh actually a lot of early computers were based on
lot of early computers were based on
lot of early computers were based on this idea and then the stack basically
this idea and then the stack basically
this idea and then the stack basically you know keeps pushing
you know keeps pushing
you know keeps pushing new things on it and uh and and then you
new things on it and uh and and then you
new things on it and uh and and then you pop and and then you read the value that
pop and and then you read the value that
pop and and then you read the value that was just
was just
was just popped.
popped.
popped. So while very basic, it still captures a
So while very basic, it still captures a
So while very basic, it still captures a lot of important programming language
lot of important programming language
lot of important programming language concepts. Now the point is that uh I
concepts. Now the point is that uh I
concepts. Now the point is that uh I want to believe that uh the mapping that
want to believe that uh the mapping that
want to believe that uh the mapping that I would do between these two
I would do between these two
I would do between these two representations is actually correct. But
representations is actually correct. But
representations is actually correct. But of course first I have to uh define the
of course first I have to uh define the
of course first I have to uh define the compiler and so this is the compiler. So
compiler and so this is the compiler. So
compiler and so this is the compiler. So what this says is that I am going to you
what this says is that I am going to you
what this says is that I am going to you know take my input expression in the
know take my input expression in the
know take my input expression in the source language and then I'm going to do
source language and then I'm going to do
source language and then I'm going to do a pattern matching. I'm going to
a pattern matching. I'm going to
a pattern matching. I'm going to consider these two cases either when
consider these two cases either when
consider these two cases either when it's a constant or when it's a binary
it's a constant or when it's a binary
it's a constant or when it's a binary operation and in each of these cases I'm
operation and in each of these cases I'm
operation and in each of these cases I'm going to you know um generate a target
going to you know um generate a target
going to you know um generate a target language program. So in the target
language program. So in the target
language program. So in the target language program the entire sequence of
language program the entire sequence of
language program the entire sequence of instructions is just written down as a
instructions is just written down as a
instructions is just written down as a list. Now it's when you are executing
list. Now it's when you are executing
list. Now it's when you are executing the program that you are maintaining a
the program that you are maintaining a
the program that you are maintaining a stack right that's when you are doing
stack right that's when you are doing
stack right that's when you are doing you know all of the kind of modeling the
you know all of the kind of modeling the
you know all of the kind of modeling the recussion. uh but in the program itself
recussion. uh but in the program itself
recussion. uh but in the program itself you are just doing this kind of a uh you
you are just doing this kind of a uh you
you are just doing this kind of a uh you you're generating the instructions from
you're generating the instructions from
you're generating the instructions from E2 you're generating the instructions
E2 you're generating the instructions
E2 you're generating the instructions from E1 and then you are sticking this B
from E1 and then you are sticking this B
from E1 and then you are sticking this B and then you are just you know building
and then you are just you know building
and then you are just you know building up a stack uh with or or a sequence of
up a stack uh with or or a sequence of
up a stack uh with or or a sequence of instructions uh with uh with all of
instructions uh with uh with all of
instructions uh with uh with all of this. So for example you know if you
this. So for example you know if you
this. So for example you know if you started with this expression you know b
started with this expression you know b
started with this expression you know b plus con 2 con 3. So this is you know 2
plus con 2 con 3. So this is you know 2
plus con 2 con 3. So this is you know 2 + 3 is that's really the expression and
+ 3 is that's really the expression and
+ 3 is that's really the expression and so then in the in the lower level
so then in the in the lower level
so then in the in the lower level language it's going to look like this.
So then you have to define this
So then you have to define this correctness theorem which says that for
correctness theorem which says that for
correctness theorem which says that for all E in the s all programs all
all E in the s all programs all
all E in the s all programs all expressions E in the source language
expressions E in the source language
expressions E in the source language upon compiling this expression you get
upon compiling this expression you get
upon compiling this expression you get something that when you execute it in
something that when you execute it in
something that when you execute it in the programming languages semantics you
the programming languages semantics you
the programming languages semantics you get the same thing as if you um if you
get the same thing as if you um if you
get the same thing as if you um if you evaluated the
evaluated the
evaluated the original expression in the source
original expression in the source
original expression in the source languages semantics right so these two
languages semantics right so these two
languages semantics right so these two are the are the
are the are the
are the are the same Now it turns out that copra cannot
same Now it turns out that copra cannot
same Now it turns out that copra cannot prove this theorem just in one shot. So
prove this theorem just in one shot. So
prove this theorem just in one shot. So what you do instead is that you ask the
what you do instead is that you ask the
what you do instead is that you ask the LLM again think of the IMO example that
LLM again think of the IMO example that
LLM again think of the IMO example that I showed this is uh quite similar. So
I showed this is uh quite similar. So
I showed this is uh quite similar. So you ask the LLM to invent a lema an
you ask the LLM to invent a lema an
you ask the LLM to invent a lema an intermediate goal. So um the LLM goes
intermediate goal. So um the LLM goes
intermediate goal. So um the LLM goes ahead and thinks for a while and this is
ahead and thinks for a while and this is
ahead and thinks for a while and this is 01 here and it comes up with this
01 here and it comes up with this
01 here and it comes up with this intermediate lema uh which basically
intermediate lema uh which basically
intermediate lema uh which basically says that rather than trying to
says that rather than trying to
says that rather than trying to prove the entire compiler correct what
prove the entire compiler correct what
prove the entire compiler correct what you instead do is that you just show you
you instead do is that you just show you
you instead do is that you just show you know one
know one
know one step of compilation like for one um one
step of compilation like for one um one
step of compilation like for one um one sub expression uh that's going to be
sub expression uh that's going to be
sub expression uh that's going to be correct.
correct.
correct. Uh so so basically that's the target
Uh so so basically that's the target
Uh so so basically that's the target theorem. The auxiliary lema is saying
theorem. The auxiliary lema is saying
theorem. The auxiliary lema is saying that you can compile you know one
that you can compile you know one
that you can compile you know one instruction correctly first. And so this
instruction correctly first. And so this
instruction correctly first. And so this is really just um simplifying the
is really just um simplifying the
is really just um simplifying the problem breaking it down in a
problem breaking it down in a
problem breaking it down in a step-by-step way and and then we ask
step-by-step way and and then we ask
step-by-step way and and then we ask Copra to come up with a proof of this
Copra to come up with a proof of this
Copra to come up with a proof of this one instruction and it's able to uh
one instruction and it's able to uh
one instruction and it's able to uh which is
which is
which is fantastic. But uh then what we can do is
fantastic. But uh then what we can do is
fantastic. But uh then what we can do is just in the way we did previously we
just in the way we did previously we
just in the way we did previously we stick this back uh we we take this proof
stick this back uh we we take this proof
stick this back uh we we take this proof give it to the the copra agent uh put it
give it to the the copra agent uh put it
give it to the the copra agent uh put it in the prompt and then ask it to you
in the prompt and then ask it to you
in the prompt and then ask it to you know prove the entire theorem correct
know prove the entire theorem correct
know prove the entire theorem correct and it's now able to do
this.
this. So that's what I uh have on this
So that's what I uh have on this
So that's what I uh have on this particular topic. Uh in summary, I would
particular topic. Uh in summary, I would
particular topic. Uh in summary, I would say that mathematical discovery with LLM
say that mathematical discovery with LLM
say that mathematical discovery with LLM agents is extremely promising.
agents is extremely promising.
agents is extremely promising. I think that you can go a very long
I think that you can go a very long
I think that you can go a very long distance with uh just uh you know in
distance with uh just uh you know in
distance with uh just uh you know in context learning. uh but uh you want to
context learning. uh but uh you want to
context learning. uh but uh you want to have the proof assistant feedback for
have the proof assistant feedback for
have the proof assistant feedback for proper grounding and there is a lot of
proper grounding and there is a lot of
proper grounding and there is a lot of you know higher level agent design that
you know higher level agent design that
you know higher level agent design that you can do where you can
you can do where you can
you can do where you can combine agents that are doing you know
combine agents that are doing you know
combine agents that are doing you know for example formalization with agents
for example formalization with agents
for example formalization with agents that are doing hierarchical planning
that are doing hierarchical planning
that are doing hierarchical planning with agents that are doing low-level uh
with agents that are doing low-level uh
with agents that are doing low-level uh stuff low-level proof generation
stuff low-level proof generation
stuff low-level proof generation um and there is uh this is a very new
um and there is uh this is a very new
um and there is uh this is a very new space there is a lot to be done over
space there is a lot to be done over
space there is a lot to be done over here
here
here Now you know one question again going
Now you know one question again going
Now you know one question again going back to something we asked
back to something we asked
back to something we asked previously. Can you get rid of this
previously. Can you get rid of this
previously. Can you get rid of this interaction by just uh pushing the whole
interaction by just uh pushing the whole
interaction by just uh pushing the whole thing to training? Maybe you know you
thing to training? Maybe you know you
thing to training? Maybe you know you generate a lot of training
generate a lot of training
generate a lot of training data in this way uh by interaction with
data in this way uh by interaction with
data in this way uh by interaction with the proofer and then you you know um
the proofer and then you you know um
the proofer and then you you know um just continue training the LLM with
just continue training the LLM with
just continue training the LLM with those traces and then at some point the
those traces and then at some point the
those traces and then at some point the LLM just gets good enough. We are not
LLM just gets good enough. We are not
LLM just gets good enough. We are not there yet. Uh but maybe this is a world
there yet. Uh but maybe this is a world
there yet. Uh but maybe this is a world that we can get to someday. Um but
that we can get to someday. Um but
that we can get to someday. Um but currently um we have to have these sorts
currently um we have to have these sorts
currently um we have to have these sorts of agent
of agent
of agent architectures. Now there's this uh paper
architectures. Now there's this uh paper
architectures. Now there's this uh paper uh several of us uh recently wrote and
uh several of us uh recently wrote and
uh several of us uh recently wrote and you may have seen a reference to this
you may have seen a reference to this
you may have seen a reference to this paper previously. Uh Caillou is the lead
paper previously. Uh Caillou is the lead
paper previously. Uh Caillou is the lead author of this um and uh Dawn was the
author of this um and uh Dawn was the
author of this um and uh Dawn was the leader of the overall effort. uh uh but
leader of the overall effort. uh uh but
leader of the overall effort. uh uh but if you are curious about this area, you
if you are curious about this area, you
if you are curious about this area, you want to uh you know know more about you
want to uh you know know more about you
want to uh you know know more about you know specific challenges road maps then
know specific challenges road maps then
know specific challenges road maps then I would recommend uh that you go and
I would recommend uh that you go and
I would recommend uh that you go and look at this
look at this
look at this paper. Um I had a few things to say
paper. Um I had a few things to say
paper. Um I had a few things to say about open challenges but I'm going to
about open challenges but I'm going to
about open challenges but I'm going to skip those in the interest of time and
skip those in the interest of time and
skip those in the interest of time and I'm going to move on to
I'm going to move on to
I'm going to move on to the uh next topic which is uh AI for
the uh next topic which is uh AI for
the uh next topic which is uh AI for scientific uh discovery uh
scientific uh discovery uh
scientific uh discovery uh because I want to emphasize that this
because I want to emphasize that this
because I want to emphasize that this idea of LLM agents this has a lot of
idea of LLM agents this has a lot of
idea of LLM agents this has a lot of value in this sort of deductive
value in this sort of deductive
value in this sort of deductive mathematics where you are starting with
mathematics where you are starting with
mathematics where you are starting with a set of principles set of axioms
a set of principles set of axioms
a set of principles set of axioms definitions
definitions
definitions and then you are proving statements in a
and then you are proving statements in a
and then you are proving statements in a step-by-step way. But it also has
step-by-step way. But it also has
step-by-step way. But it also has tremendous potential in empirical
tremendous potential in empirical
tremendous potential in empirical discovery which is what happens in most
discovery which is what happens in most
discovery which is what happens in most of the natural sciences where you are uh
of the natural sciences where you are uh
of the natural sciences where you are uh starting with data and then you are
starting with data and then you are
starting with data and then you are trying to fit
trying to fit
trying to fit um you know some hypothesis uh or or
um you know some hypothesis uh or or
um you know some hypothesis uh or or some uh some experimental cla or some
some uh some experimental cla or some
some uh some experimental cla or some some claims to this data. Um now we'll
some claims to this data. Um now we'll
some claims to this data. Um now we'll see that this is also a place where the
see that this is also a place where the
see that this is also a place where the abstraction abilities of LLMs uh play a
abstraction abilities of LLMs uh play a
abstraction abilities of LLMs uh play a potentially very interesting
potentially very interesting
potentially very interesting role. Okay. So very quickly
role. Okay. So very quickly
role. Okay. So very quickly um this is what a natural science
um this is what a natural science
um this is what a natural science process looks like. you know, you choose
process looks like. you know, you choose
process looks like. you know, you choose a research question, you generate some
a research question, you generate some
a research question, you generate some hypothesis, you uh do an experimental
hypothesis, you uh do an experimental
hypothesis, you uh do an experimental setup, you collect some data, you do
setup, you collect some data, you do
setup, you collect some data, you do some analysis of the data, you interpret
some analysis of the data, you interpret
some analysis of the data, you interpret the data, and then you report to the
the data, and then you report to the
the data, and then you report to the community, right? And
community, right? And
community, right? And um and so uh just as an example of this,
um and so uh just as an example of this,
um and so uh just as an example of this, you know, if you think of the uh world
you know, if you think of the uh world
you know, if you think of the uh world of
of
of astronomy, back in the day, there was
astronomy, back in the day, there was
astronomy, back in the day, there was this problem uh that was uh observed
this problem uh that was uh observed
this problem uh that was uh observed which is that people believed that the
which is that people believed that the
which is that people believed that the the earth was the center of the solar
the earth was the center of the solar
the earth was the center of the solar system, but then some of the planets
system, but then some of the planets
system, but then some of the planets appear to move backward. And so this led
appear to move backward. And so this led
appear to move backward. And so this led to this creation of this new hypothesis
to this creation of this new hypothesis
to this creation of this new hypothesis that in fact we have a heliocentric
that in fact we have a heliocentric
that in fact we have a heliocentric model and then this led to the creation
model and then this led to the creation
model and then this led to the creation uh the collection of more data. Uh Taiko
uh the collection of more data. Uh Taiko
uh the collection of more data. Uh Taiko Brahe in particular observed Mars and
Brahe in particular observed Mars and
Brahe in particular observed Mars and then uh came up with a whole bunch of
then uh came up with a whole bunch of
then uh came up with a whole bunch of precise measurements of the planet's
precise measurements of the planet's
precise measurements of the planet's positions.
positions.
positions. um and then um Kepler chose to analyze
um and then um Kepler chose to analyze
um and then um Kepler chose to analyze this data and then fit a wide variety of
this data and then fit a wide variety of
this data and then fit a wide variety of geometric shapes to this data and then
geometric shapes to this data and then
geometric shapes to this data and then he came up with this Kepler's third law.
he came up with this Kepler's third law.
he came up with this Kepler's third law. Um and then this eventually led to uh
Um and then this eventually led to uh
Um and then this eventually led to uh Newton's law of gravitation. Uh so there
Newton's law of gravitation. Uh so there
Newton's law of gravitation. Uh so there was this process that happened in
was this process that happened in
was this process that happened in science which uh involved trading in
science which uh involved trading in
science which uh involved trading in abstractions you know uh seeing some
abstractions you know uh seeing some
abstractions you know uh seeing some data and then coming up with this uh
data and then coming up with this uh
data and then coming up with this uh this this law in terms of abstract
this this law in terms of abstract
this this law in terms of abstract principles uh but then you know further
principles uh but then you know further
principles uh but then you know further generalizing it into a law that was even
generalizing it into a law that was even
generalizing it into a law that was even more
more
more explanatory. So I think that LLM agents
explanatory. So I think that LLM agents
explanatory. So I think that LLM agents have tremendous potential in automating
have tremendous potential in automating
have tremendous potential in automating a lot of pieces of this pipeline and in
a lot of pieces of this pipeline and in
a lot of pieces of this pipeline and in particular here we are going to focus on
particular here we are going to focus on
particular here we are going to focus on the problem of symbolic regression which
the problem of symbolic regression which
the problem of symbolic regression which is uh the task of coming up with
is uh the task of coming up with
is uh the task of coming up with equations based on empirical
equations based on empirical
equations based on empirical observations.
observations.
observations. Uh so for
Uh so for
Uh so for example an instance of that would be
example an instance of that would be
example an instance of that would be that if you were given these
that if you were given these
that if you were given these measurements of planet
measurements of planet
measurements of planet Mars and then uh you wanted to discover
Mars and then uh you wanted to discover
Mars and then uh you wanted to discover Kepler's law how do you do that right
Kepler's law how do you do that right
Kepler's law how do you do that right from the
from the
from the data now one would think that LMS would
data now one would think that LMS would
data now one would think that LMS would not be a great fit for this problem
not be a great fit for this problem
not be a great fit for this problem because the data is just really low
because the data is just really low
because the data is just really low level right this is just a bunch of
level right this is just a bunch of
level right this is just a bunch of numbers however it turns Turns out uh
numbers however it turns Turns out uh
numbers however it turns Turns out uh that LLMs uh do have a tremendous
that LLMs uh do have a tremendous
that LLMs uh do have a tremendous potential over here in the sense that uh
potential over here in the sense that uh
potential over here in the sense that uh they can bring in prior scientific
they can bring in prior scientific
they can bring in prior scientific knowledge into the picture. What you
knowledge into the picture. What you
knowledge into the picture. What you have to do though is that you have to
have to do though is that you have to
have to do though is that you have to complement the use of LLMs with the use
complement the use of LLMs with the use
complement the use of LLMs with the use of other machinery that is able to for
of other machinery that is able to for
of other machinery that is able to for example evaluate hypothesis on the data
example evaluate hypothesis on the data
example evaluate hypothesis on the data and uh give you uh some notion of how
and uh give you uh some notion of how
and uh give you uh some notion of how well it performed.
well it performed.
well it performed. So once you have that kind of a
So once you have that kind of a
So once you have that kind of a mechanism for evaluating LLM generated
mechanism for evaluating LLM generated
mechanism for evaluating LLM generated hypothesis, you can create an agentic
hypothesis, you can create an agentic
hypothesis, you can create an agentic loop where you have more and more
loop where you have more and more
loop where you have more and more feedback going to the LLM and then uh
feedback going to the LLM and then uh
feedback going to the LLM and then uh you know this process of hypothesis
you know this process of hypothesis
you know this process of hypothesis generation is left to the LLM whereas
generation is left to the LLM whereas
generation is left to the LLM whereas you know hypothesis evaluation is done
you know hypothesis evaluation is done
you know hypothesis evaluation is done by some some other um entity and if you
by some some other um entity and if you
by some some other um entity and if you think of it it's not fundamentally
think of it it's not fundamentally
think of it it's not fundamentally different from the way we use lean or or
different from the way we use lean or or
different from the way we use lean or or the proof assistant in the previous part
the proof assistant in the previous part
the proof assistant in the previous part of the
lecture. So, uh
lecture. So, uh the one of the most established
the one of the most established
the one of the most established approaches to symbolic regression is
approaches to symbolic regression is
approaches to symbolic regression is genetic programming and the here are
genetic programming and the here are
genetic programming and the here are some visualizations from a system called
some visualizations from a system called
some visualizations from a system called Pyer which is quite popular in this
Pyer which is quite popular in this
Pyer which is quite popular in this space. And so what's going on here is
space. And so what's going on here is
space. And so what's going on here is that you have a pool of candidate
that you have a pool of candidate
that you have a pool of candidate expressions, candidate equations being
expressions, candidate equations being
expressions, candidate equations being maintained and then you have um mutation
maintained and then you have um mutation
maintained and then you have um mutation and crossover operations being applied
and crossover operations being applied
and crossover operations being applied to those and then uh you know you are
to those and then uh you know you are
to those and then uh you know you are generating you're updating this this
generating you're updating this this
generating you're updating this this pool of expressions using feedback from
pool of expressions using feedback from
pool of expressions using feedback from a separate machinery that is evaluating
a separate machinery that is evaluating
a separate machinery that is evaluating these expressions and telling you you
these expressions and telling you you
these expressions and telling you you know how good is the loss, how well does
know how good is the loss, how well does
know how good is the loss, how well does this uh match the match the reality that
this uh match the match the reality that
this uh match the match the reality that is there in the
data. So uh this has had a lot of
data. So uh this has had a lot of impact. Uh there are applications in you
impact. Uh there are applications in you
impact. Uh there are applications in you know physics and uh other areas as well.
know physics and uh other areas as well.
know physics and uh other areas as well. And um so here are some example papers.
And um so here are some example papers.
And um so here are some example papers. Um so um one thing that's interesting is
Um so um one thing that's interesting is
Um so um one thing that's interesting is that if you just imagine how does this
that if you just imagine how does this
that if you just imagine how does this process
process
process of genetic programming go on. So there
of genetic programming go on. So there
of genetic programming go on. So there is this pool of expressions that is
is this pool of expressions that is
is this pool of expressions that is being evolved. And so what you see is
being evolved. And so what you see is
being evolved. And so what you see is that there are these uh you know islands
that there are these uh you know islands
that there are these uh you know islands of expressions. So these clusters which
of expressions. So these clusters which
of expressions. So these clusters which uh contain expressions that are of um
uh contain expressions that are of um
uh contain expressions that are of um that have something in common between
that have something in common between
that have something in common between them. Um so
them. Um so
them. Um so the one way to think about how LLMs are
the one way to think about how LLMs are
the one way to think about how LLMs are relevant is that these clusters or
relevant is that these clusters or
relevant is that these clusters or islands of expressions these capture
islands of expressions these capture
islands of expressions these capture various kinds of you know various
various kinds of you know various
various kinds of you know various classes of functions. So for example you
classes of functions. So for example you
classes of functions. So for example you know in this red one over here you may
know in this red one over here you may
know in this red one over here you may have exponential functions. Um in this
have exponential functions. Um in this
have exponential functions. Um in this case you may have trigonometric
case you may have trigonometric
case you may have trigonometric functions uh where you have the
functions uh where you have the
functions uh where you have the cosiness and so so one way to imagine
cosiness and so so one way to imagine
cosiness and so so one way to imagine this is that an LLM um looking at these
this is that an LLM um looking at these
this is that an LLM um looking at these these uh expressions because LLMs are
these uh expressions because LLMs are
these uh expressions because LLMs are good at coding and associating code with
good at coding and associating code with
good at coding and associating code with natural language could perhaps come up
natural language could perhaps come up
natural language could perhaps come up with you know some explanation of what
with you know some explanation of what
with you know some explanation of what this piece of code this expression is
this piece of code this expression is
this piece of code this expression is actually doing right and that's the idea
actually doing right and that's the idea
actually doing right and that's the idea of abstraction that we are going to
of abstraction that we are going to
of abstraction that we are going to Okay. Uh so this paper uh was at Nurips
Okay. Uh so this paper uh was at Nurips
Okay. Uh so this paper uh was at Nurips last year and uh co-led by Arya Gley who
last year and uh co-led by Arya Gley who
last year and uh co-led by Arya Gley who was an undergrad at UT and Aurva Seagal
was an undergrad at UT and Aurva Seagal
was an undergrad at UT and Aurva Seagal who's a PhD student um at UT and uh
who's a PhD student um at UT and uh
who's a PhD student um at UT and uh so so the starting point here is that we
so so the starting point here is that we
so so the starting point here is that we want to do this kind of concept
want to do this kind of concept
want to do this kind of concept abstraction and so um what we want to be
abstraction and so um what we want to be
abstraction and so um what we want to be able to do is that we want to look at
able to do is that we want to look at
able to do is that we want to look at you know these variety of laws uh which
you know these variety of laws uh which
you know these variety of laws uh which come from very different contexts. But
come from very different contexts. But
come from very different contexts. But then, you know, we should be able to
then, you know, we should be able to
then, you know, we should be able to look at this and kind of tell that
look at this and kind of tell that
look at this and kind of tell that what's going on here is that you have,
what's going on here is that you have,
what's going on here is that you have, you know, this power law thing going on.
you know, this power law thing going on.
you know, this power law thing going on. All right. Um, and uh, so, uh, the other
All right. Um, and uh, so, uh, the other
All right. Um, and uh, so, uh, the other thing we want to do is that we want to
thing we want to do is that we want to
thing we want to do is that we want to use background knowledge that was
use background knowledge that was
use background knowledge that was created by a physicist or that's there
created by a physicist or that's there
created by a physicist or that's there inside an LLM. Um so for example here
inside an LLM. Um so for example here
inside an LLM. Um so for example here you have you know an LLM uh a a concept
you have you know an LLM uh a a concept
you have you know an LLM uh a a concept that has been produced which is that you
that has been produced which is that you
that has been produced which is that you know wave strain diminishes as distance
know wave strain diminishes as distance
know wave strain diminishes as distance increases. This is a let's say property
increases. This is a let's say property
increases. This is a let's say property of you know the
of you know the
of you know the um of black holes and so you want to be
um of black holes and so you want to be
um of black holes and so you want to be able to
able to
able to associate this kind of um information
associate this kind of um information
associate this kind of um information you know this is a piece of common sense
you know this is a piece of common sense
you know this is a piece of common sense knowledge to equations. Um so this
knowledge to equations. Um so this
knowledge to equations. Um so this equation for example satisfies these
equation for example satisfies these
equation for example satisfies these properties but um this is you want to
properties but um this is you want to
properties but um this is you want to create a mapping between these two
create a mapping between these two
create a mapping between these two things and because you know if you
things and because you know if you
things and because you know if you imagine how the scientific process is
imagine how the scientific process is
imagine how the scientific process is ongoing so let's say you have an AI that
ongoing so let's say you have an AI that
ongoing so let's say you have an AI that is predicting equations based on data
is predicting equations based on data
is predicting equations based on data you also want it to be conditioned on
you also want it to be conditioned on
you also want it to be conditioned on this sort of highle knowledge that is
this sort of highle knowledge that is
this sort of highle knowledge that is being given by a human expert right and
being given by a human expert right and
being given by a human expert right and so so you want to have this association
so so you want to have this association
so so you want to have this association between between code that is these
between between code that is these
between between code that is these equations and and
equations and and
equations and and language.
language.
language. Um
Um
Um so the way we set up this symbolic
so the way we set up this symbolic
so the way we set up this symbolic regression problem using um LLMs is
regression problem using um LLMs is
regression problem using um LLMs is something like this that we
something like this that we
something like this that we imagine that um and and actually here
imagine that um and and actually here
imagine that um and and actually here it's not just LLMs it's more like you
it's not just LLMs it's more like you
it's not just LLMs it's more like you know a combination of LLMs and this sort
know a combination of LLMs and this sort
know a combination of LLMs and this sort of um abstraction into high level
of um abstraction into high level
of um abstraction into high level concepts uh and and so we imagine that
concepts uh and and so we imagine that
concepts uh and and so we imagine that there is this universe of highle
there is this universe of highle
there is this universe of highle concepts. So for example you know wave
concepts. So for example you know wave
concepts. So for example you know wave strain diminishes as distance increases
strain diminishes as distance increases
strain diminishes as distance increases or power laws or cinosidal functions
or power laws or cinosidal functions
or power laws or cinosidal functions these are sort of highle ideas that we
these are sort of highle ideas that we
these are sort of highle ideas that we have in our head and there is a notion
have in our head and there is a notion
have in our head and there is a notion of a data set which is the concrete data
of a data set which is the concrete data
of a data set which is the concrete data uh that you want to fit and then you
uh that you want to fit and then you
uh that you want to fit and then you have a space of programmatic hypothesis.
have a space of programmatic hypothesis.
have a space of programmatic hypothesis. This this is for example the you know
This this is for example the you know
This this is for example the you know the the landscape of equation or the set
the the landscape of equation or the set
the the landscape of equation or the set of equations expressible in Python or or
of equations expressible in Python or or
of equations expressible in Python or or you know in some restricted DSL inside
you know in some restricted DSL inside
you know in some restricted DSL inside Python and then what you're saying is
Python and then what you're saying is
Python and then what you're saying is that you want to jointly infer given the
that you want to jointly infer given the
that you want to jointly infer given the data uh this uh distribution over pi
data uh this uh distribution over pi
data uh this uh distribution over pi which is you know likely hypothesis and
which is you know likely hypothesis and
which is you know likely hypothesis and likely concepts. So you don't want to
likely concepts. So you don't want to
likely concepts. So you don't want to just get likely programs given the data
just get likely programs given the data
just get likely programs given the data which would be the goal of traditional
which would be the goal of traditional
which would be the goal of traditional symbolic regression. You want to get
symbolic regression. You want to get
symbolic regression. You want to get both the programs and also the kinds of
both the programs and also the kinds of
both the programs and also the kinds of concepts that they represent because
concepts that they represent because
concepts that they represent because ultimately you want to explain these
ultimately you want to explain these
ultimately you want to explain these programs to a human uh scientist or
programs to a human uh scientist or
programs to a human uh scientist or alternatively maybe you know this joint
alternatively maybe you know this joint
alternatively maybe you know this joint distribution gives you more more
distribution gives you more more
distribution gives you more more information than if you just operated in
information than if you just operated in
information than if you just operated in the program
the program
the program space. And so this you can factoriize in
space. And so this you can factoriize in
space. And so this you can factoriize in this way. And then um it uh turns out
this way. And then um it uh turns out
this way. And then um it uh turns out that you know um the way to think about
that you know um the way to think about
that you know um the way to think about it is that uh p of d given pi is
it is that uh p of d given pi is
it is that uh p of d given pi is basically saying that if I have a
basically saying that if I have a
basically saying that if I have a particular program pi what is
particular program pi what is
particular program pi what is the likelihood of the data. So you know
the likelihood of the data. So you know
the likelihood of the data. So you know how well does the program explain the
how well does the program explain the
how well does the program explain the data? In order to find this, you just
data? In order to find this, you just
data? In order to find this, you just execute the program, right? And see what
execute the program, right? And see what
execute the program, right? And see what kinds of results come out and if it what
kinds of results come out and if it what
kinds of results come out and if it what the likelihood of the data set is. And
the likelihood of the data set is. And
the likelihood of the data set is. And uh P of pi given C is basically telling
uh P of pi given C is basically telling
uh P of pi given C is basically telling telling you that okay here are these um
telling you that okay here are these um
telling you that okay here are these um these uh con here is a concept that I
these uh con here is a concept that I
these uh con here is a concept that I have. So let's say I'm thinking about
have. So let's say I'm thinking about
have. So let's say I'm thinking about power laws. Okay. So conditioned on this
power laws. Okay. So conditioned on this
power laws. Okay. So conditioned on this concept that I'm thinking about power
concept that I'm thinking about power
concept that I'm thinking about power laws. what is the probability of this
laws. what is the probability of this
laws. what is the probability of this program that uh you know this piece of
program that uh you know this piece of
program that uh you know this piece of code right uh to what extent does this
code right uh to what extent does this
code right uh to what extent does this piece of code represent a power law and
piece of code represent a power law and
piece of code represent a power law and this is something that an LLM has
this is something that an LLM has
this is something that an LLM has background knowledge inside it to do and
background knowledge inside it to do and
background knowledge inside it to do and then finally I have this PFC which is a
then finally I have this PFC which is a
then finally I have this PFC which is a prior concepts and this is also
prior concepts and this is also
prior concepts and this is also something that an LLM knows that you
something that an LLM knows that you
something that an LLM knows that you know I have seen the literature of let's
know I have seen the literature of let's
know I have seen the literature of let's say physics until this point so what is
say physics until this point so what is
say physics until this point so what is the likelihood of this concept concept,
the likelihood of this concept concept,
the likelihood of this concept concept, right? Um
right? Um
right? Um so all of this together gives you
so all of this together gives you
so all of this together gives you ultimately the ability to infer uh both
ultimately the ability to infer uh both
ultimately the ability to infer uh both um a distribution over a distribution
um a distribution over a distribution
um a distribution over a distribution over both programs and and
over both programs and and
over both programs and and concepts. Now in order to really
concepts. Now in order to really
concepts. Now in order to really implement this uh this is the loop that
implement this uh this is the loop that
implement this uh this is the loop that we came up with. Uh so this follows the
we came up with. Uh so this follows the
we came up with. Uh so this follows the basic structure of an evolutionary
basic structure of an evolutionary
basic structure of an evolutionary algorithm but it does this sort of uh
algorithm but it does this sort of uh
algorithm but it does this sort of uh you know this sort of basian concept
you know this sort of basian concept
you know this sort of basian concept learning thing uh guided by LLMs on on
learning thing uh guided by LLMs on on
learning thing uh guided by LLMs on on top of
top of
top of that and so operationally the way to
that and so operationally the way to
that and so operationally the way to think about it is that you have a like
think about it is that you have a like
think about it is that you have a like in any evolutionary algorithm you're
in any evolutionary algorithm you're
in any evolutionary algorithm you're maintaining a population of hypothesis
maintaining a population of hypothesis
maintaining a population of hypothesis or
or
or programs and then at this point you have
programs and then at this point you have
programs and then at this point you have a choice of doing you know um evolution
a choice of doing you know um evolution
a choice of doing you know um evolution either guided by the classical symbolic
either guided by the classical symbolic
either guided by the classical symbolic method where you're doing some random
method where you're doing some random
method where you're doing some random tweaks to the abstract syntax tree of
tweaks to the abstract syntax tree of
tweaks to the abstract syntax tree of the program or alternatively you are
the program or alternatively you are
the program or alternatively you are doing this LLM guided evolution where
doing this LLM guided evolution where
doing this LLM guided evolution where you are saying that here is a concept
you are saying that here is a concept
you are saying that here is a concept here is a program that I have and I want
here is a program that I have and I want
here is a program that I have and I want to generate a new program and when
to generate a new program and when
to generate a new program and when you're doing that you are being guided
you're doing that you are being guided
you're doing that you are being guided by this concept library which tells you
by this concept library which tells you
by this concept library which tells you that you know these are the concepts
that you know these are the concepts
that you know these are the concepts that I'm thinking about right now right
that I'm thinking about right now right
that I'm thinking about right now right so power laws seem really good uh really
so power laws seem really good uh really
so power laws seem really good uh really well suited to this condition uh this
well suited to this condition uh this
well suited to this condition uh this concept or or this setting or you know
concept or or this setting or you know
concept or or this setting or you know maybe um uh trigonometric functions seem
maybe um uh trigonometric functions seem
maybe um uh trigonometric functions seem especially well suited to this setting
especially well suited to this setting
especially well suited to this setting and so on right so you are feeding all
and so on right so you are feeding all
and so on right so you are feeding all of that to this LLM guided evolution
of that to this LLM guided evolution
of that to this LLM guided evolution process and that allows you to you know
process and that allows you to you know
process and that allows you to you know basically mutate the current
basically mutate the current
basically mutate the current programs into new
programs into new
programs into new programs and then after you do that you
programs and then after you do that you
programs and then after you do that you are like in the usual evolutionary way
are like in the usual evolutionary way
are like in the usual evolutionary way you are identifying the best candidates
you are identifying the best candidates
you are identifying the best candidates in in this population. Um and so this is
in in this population. Um and so this is
in in this population. Um and so this is where you use the fitness function which
where you use the fitness function which
where you use the fitness function which is you know how well do your do your um
is you know how well do your do your um
is you know how well do your do your um does your uh hypothesis pool explain the
does your uh hypothesis pool explain the
does your uh hypothesis pool explain the data that you have right and this is
data that you have right and this is
data that you have right and this is where that p of d given pi that comes in
where that p of d given pi that comes in
where that p of d given pi that comes in um and so this is a little bit more
um and so this is a little bit more
um and so this is a little bit more detail about how the hypothesis
detail about how the hypothesis
detail about how the hypothesis evaluation evolution works. Uh so you
evaluation evolution works. Uh so you
evaluation evolution works. Uh so you know you start with this initialization
know you start with this initialization
know you start with this initialization initial program population and then
initial program population and then
initial program population and then you're evaluating you're getting the
you're evaluating you're getting the
you're evaluating you're getting the best program you're mutating or crossing
best program you're mutating or crossing
best program you're mutating or crossing over and then you are um you're
over and then you are um you're
over and then you are um you're replacing the oldest program and then
replacing the oldest program and then
replacing the oldest program and then this process just carries on uh for a
this process just carries on uh for a
this process just carries on uh for a while. Uh so the important thing over
while. Uh so the important thing over
while. Uh so the important thing over here is that you are using the LLM for
here is that you are using the LLM for
here is that you are using the LLM for implementing this mutation and crossover
implementing this mutation and crossover
implementing this mutation and crossover operations. So in particular rather than
operations. So in particular rather than
operations. So in particular rather than you know um in a classical genetic
you know um in a classical genetic
you know um in a classical genetic algorithm what's going to happen is that
algorithm what's going to happen is that
algorithm what's going to happen is that you're given the a and you're going to
you're given the a and you're going to
you're given the a and you're going to say that okay swap out this sub tree by
say that okay swap out this sub tree by
say that okay swap out this sub tree by a different sub tree. Now you're going
a different sub tree. Now you're going
a different sub tree. Now you're going to say that I'm going to ask the LLM to
to say that I'm going to ask the LLM to
to say that I'm going to ask the LLM to rewrite the program into something. And
rewrite the program into something. And
rewrite the program into something. And this idea was also used in um the fund
this idea was also used in um the fund
this idea was also used in um the fund search paper from uh deep mind last
search paper from uh deep mind last
search paper from uh deep mind last year. And uh fun search uh has been very
year. And uh fun search uh has been very
year. And uh fun search uh has been very successful. The way in which the this
successful. The way in which the this
successful. The way in which the this laser work differs from fun search uh is
laser work differs from fun search uh is
laser work differs from fun search uh is fundamental in its use of this concept
fundamental in its use of this concept
fundamental in its use of this concept library. But a lot of the other ideas
library. But a lot of the other ideas
library. But a lot of the other ideas are are uh closely related.
are are uh closely related.
are are uh closely related. Um so this is just to highlight you know
Um so this is just to highlight you know
Um so this is just to highlight you know the difference between the symbolic
the difference between the symbolic
the difference between the symbolic crossover versus the LLM crossover. So
crossover versus the LLM crossover. So
crossover versus the LLM crossover. So in this case the LLM is basically doing
in this case the LLM is basically doing
in this case the LLM is basically doing all this. Uh it's being given a
all this. Uh it's being given a
all this. Uh it's being given a crossover prompt and then it's given
crossover prompt and then it's given
crossover prompt and then it's given some formatting instructions and then
some formatting instructions and then
some formatting instructions and then it's generating the new
it's generating the new
it's generating the new expression. So after you do this um
expression. So after you do this um
expression. So after you do this um there is the so you have evolved your
there is the so you have evolved your
there is the so you have evolved your hypothesis. So now you have this new
hypothesis. So now you have this new
hypothesis. So now you have this new pool and now you also evolve your
pool and now you also evolve your
pool and now you also evolve your concept library. And so the concept
concept library. And so the concept
concept library. And so the concept library uh uh this evolution process has
library uh uh this evolution process has
library uh uh this evolution process has these two stages. So first you know you
these two stages. So first you know you
these two stages. So first you know you take your new programs that you've
take your new programs that you've
take your new programs that you've created your new program pool and now
created your new program pool and now
created your new program pool and now you're asking the LLM to abstract this
you're asking the LLM to abstract this
you're asking the LLM to abstract this into these sort of natural language
into these sort of natural language
into these sort of natural language highle descriptions. So for example here
highle descriptions. So for example here
highle descriptions. So for example here the LLM is telling you that oh this
the LLM is telling you that oh this
the LLM is telling you that oh this equation represents exponential growth
equation represents exponential growth
equation represents exponential growth or
or
or decay. And then the LLM uh the concept
decay. And then the LLM uh the concept
decay. And then the LLM uh the concept evolution process is just like the
evolution process is just like the
evolution process is just like the hypothesis or program evaluation
hypothesis or program evaluation
hypothesis or program evaluation evolution process except it now uses
evolution process except it now uses
evolution process except it now uses this uh u you know an LLM to basically u
this uh u you know an LLM to basically u
this uh u you know an LLM to basically u combine mash up these different concepts
combine mash up these different concepts
combine mash up these different concepts into a new concept. So for example here
into a new concept. So for example here
into a new concept. So for example here you see that you know exponential growth
you see that you know exponential growth
you see that you know exponential growth decay this is one concept another
decay this is one concept another
decay this is one concept another concept says depend on depends on
concept says depend on depends on
concept says depend on depends on temperature and our LLM because it has
temperature and our LLM because it has
temperature and our LLM because it has all this knowledge about all sorts of
all this knowledge about all sorts of
all this knowledge about all sorts of concepts relevant in physics it comes up
concepts relevant in physics it comes up
concepts relevant in physics it comes up with this idea that oh you know this uh
with this idea that oh you know this uh
with this idea that oh you know this uh should be a Boltzman distribution this
should be a Boltzman distribution this
should be a Boltzman distribution this is a useful concept to have and then
is a useful concept to have and then
is a useful concept to have and then this is going to influence the
this is going to influence the
this is going to influence the hypothesis evolution which is going to
hypothesis evolution which is going to
hypothesis evolution which is going to influence concept abstraction and
influence concept abstraction and
influence concept abstraction and evolution and this loop will
evolution and this loop will
evolution and this loop will continue. So um one way to uh visualize
continue. So um one way to uh visualize
continue. So um one way to uh visualize this is that after the first phase when
this is that after the first phase when
this is that after the first phase when you have done this hypothesis evolution
you have done this hypothesis evolution
you have done this hypothesis evolution you may have these you know islands of
you may have these you know islands of
you may have these you know islands of different kinds of
different kinds of
different kinds of expressions. Now in the uh
expressions. Now in the uh
expressions. Now in the uh concept generation process concept
concept generation process concept
concept generation process concept discovery process uh you're going to get
discovery process uh you're going to get
discovery process uh you're going to get these you know natural language
these you know natural language
these you know natural language descriptions of these different islands.
descriptions of these different islands.
descriptions of these different islands. So this is sinosidal trends, this is
So this is sinosidal trends, this is
So this is sinosidal trends, this is power law trends, this is linear trends,
power law trends, this is linear trends,
power law trends, this is linear trends, this is exponential trends and so on.
this is exponential trends and so on.
this is exponential trends and so on. And um then um what we found is that the
And um then um what we found is that the
And um then um what we found is that the use of this sort of a highle concept
use of this sort of a highle concept
use of this sort of a highle concept library helped us in this equation
library helped us in this equation
library helped us in this equation discovery process. So we evaluated this
discovery process. So we evaluated this
discovery process. So we evaluated this on this task of you know equation
on this task of you know equation
on this task of you know equation discovery um or discovering fineman
discovery um or discovering fineman
discovery um or discovering fineman equations just given the the uh prompt
equations just given the the uh prompt
equations just given the the uh prompt that so there was the data but then
that so there was the data but then
that so there was the data but then there was a prompt that uh told you you
there was a prompt that uh told you you
there was a prompt that uh told you you know which chapter you were looking at
know which chapter you were looking at
know which chapter you were looking at and and so on. And so what we found is
and and so on. And so what we found is
and and so on. And so what we found is that uh this uh approach proved more
that uh this uh approach proved more
that uh this uh approach proved more effective than a version where you were
effective than a version where you were
effective than a version where you were just using either pure genetic
just using either pure genetic
just using either pure genetic programming or one where uh you were not
programming or one where uh you were not
programming or one where uh you were not using uh any kind of concept learning.
using uh any kind of concept learning.
using uh any kind of concept learning. And um so the so uh it turns out that
And um so the so uh it turns out that
And um so the so uh it turns out that even with local language models when we
even with local language models when we
even with local language models when we didn't use a frontier model uh we were
didn't use a frontier model uh we were
didn't use a frontier model uh we were still able to outperform uh this uh
still able to outperform uh this uh
still able to outperform uh this uh genetic programming approach and um and
genetic programming approach and um and
genetic programming approach and um and the overall finding was that uh and you
the overall finding was that uh and you
the overall finding was that uh and you can find more details in the paper is
can find more details in the paper is
can find more details in the paper is that the use of this sort of highle
that the use of this sort of highle
that the use of this sort of highle concepts generated by the LLM it
concepts generated by the LLM it
concepts generated by the LLM it accelerates uh
accelerates uh
accelerates uh discovery. Now one appeal of this sort
discovery. Now one appeal of this sort
discovery. Now one appeal of this sort of um
of um
of um um LLM based approach is that it can
um LLM based approach is that it can
um LLM based approach is that it can very naturally take in user provided
very naturally take in user provided
very naturally take in user provided hints. So in this case uh we uh gave the
hints. So in this case uh we uh gave the
hints. So in this case uh we uh gave the uh the um algorithm some hints which was
uh the um algorithm some hints which was
uh the um algorithm some hints which was you know uh this is the kind of equation
you know uh this is the kind of equation
you know uh this is the kind of equation you are looking at. Uh so in the
you are looking at. Uh so in the
you are looking at. Uh so in the previous uh experiments actually we did
previous uh experiments actually we did
previous uh experiments actually we did not have hints. So this was just you
not have hints. So this was just you
not have hints. So this was just you know purely based on data but then uh in
know purely based on data but then uh in
know purely based on data but then uh in this case we had hints and then we found
this case we had hints and then we found
this case we had hints and then we found that hints actually uh provided uh some
that hints actually uh provided uh some
that hints actually uh provided uh some benefits. So on the x-axis here you have
benefits. So on the x-axis here you have
benefits. So on the x-axis here you have the number of iterations on the y-axis
the number of iterations on the y-axis
the number of iterations on the y-axis you have the you know the fraction of
you have the you know the fraction of
you have the you know the fraction of equation solved and then we found that
equation solved and then we found that
equation solved and then we found that the use of the hint said it provided a
the use of the hint said it provided a
the use of the hint said it provided a modest benefit uh at least earlier on in
modest benefit uh at least earlier on in
modest benefit uh at least earlier on in the process.
the process.
the process. So here is an example of this in action.
So here is an example of this in action.
So here is an example of this in action. Uh so um here this is the classic
Uh so um here this is the classic
Uh so um here this is the classic kulum's law and then um pyer is this
kulum's law and then um pyer is this
kulum's law and then um pyer is this genetic programming approach and um it
genetic programming approach and um it
genetic programming approach and um it gave this very unwieldy kind of
gave this very unwieldy kind of
gave this very unwieldy kind of expression um that it turns out is
expression um that it turns out is
expression um that it turns out is equivalent to the ground truth
equivalent to the ground truth
equivalent to the ground truth expression but it required a lot of
expression but it required a lot of
expression but it required a lot of simplification uh for you to it would
simplification uh for you to it would
simplification uh for you to it would require a lot of simplification for you
require a lot of simplification for you
require a lot of simplification for you to go from here to the ground truth
to go from here to the ground truth
to go from here to the ground truth whereas the laser approach approach uh
whereas the laser approach approach uh
whereas the laser approach approach uh is able to uh basically
is able to uh basically
is able to uh basically uh because of the uh you know some of
uh because of the uh you know some of
uh because of the uh you know some of the knowledge that is there in the LLM
the knowledge that is there in the LLM
the knowledge that is there in the LLM it's able to you know reduce to ground
it's able to you know reduce to ground
it's able to you know reduce to ground truth after four steps of simplification
truth after four steps of simplification
truth after four steps of simplification now you could say wait a second isn't
now you could say wait a second isn't
now you could say wait a second isn't the LLM cheating because it already has
the LLM cheating because it already has
the LLM cheating because it already has kulum's law in its mind so how do you
kulum's law in its mind so how do you
kulum's law in its mind so how do you know that this is not just you know
know that this is not just you know
know that this is not just you know leakage and of course in this case there
leakage and of course in this case there
leakage and of course in this case there is that possibility but that said I
is that possibility but that said I
is that possibility but that said I would say that you know the attraction
would say that you know the attraction
would say that you know the attraction here is that the input to the system is
here is that the input to the system is
here is that the input to the system is just this data right uh it's just the
just this data right uh it's just the
just this data right uh it's just the input output values uh for that would
input output values uh for that would
input output values uh for that would result from kulum's law and it's a very
result from kulum's law and it's a very
result from kulum's law and it's a very low-level kind of input the fact that it
low-level kind of input the fact that it
low-level kind of input the fact that it was able to fit this to kulum's law is
was able to fit this to kulum's law is
was able to fit this to kulum's law is is kind of interesting but that said we
is kind of interesting but that said we
is kind of interesting but that said we also did other experiments on synthetic
also did other experiments on synthetic
also did other experiments on synthetic data uh where you just manufactured a
data uh where you just manufactured a
data uh where you just manufactured a completely uh weird equation and a weird
completely uh weird equation and a weird
completely uh weird equation and a weird data set uh coming from that equation
data set uh coming from that equation
data set uh coming from that equation and then asked the system to to
and then asked the system to to
and then asked the system to to regenerate this and we found that there
regenerate this and we found that there
regenerate this and we found that there were substantial benefits even in that
were substantial benefits even in that
were substantial benefits even in that case. So um here is some information
case. So um here is some information
case. So um here is some information about some of the concepts that you
about some of the concepts that you
about some of the concepts that you ended up getting from from laser. So you
ended up getting from from laser. So you
ended up getting from from laser. So you see there is stuff like you know good
see there is stuff like you know good
see there is stuff like you know good mathematical expressions exhibit
mathematical expressions exhibit
mathematical expressions exhibit symmetry or regularity but that said
symmetry or regularity but that said
symmetry or regularity but that said there were also some expressions that
there were also some expressions that
there were also some expressions that were really um that didn't really seem
were really um that didn't really seem
were really um that didn't really seem to mean
to mean
to mean anything. Um but at the same time you
anything. Um but at the same time you
anything. Um but at the same time you know there is no guarantee about the
know there is no guarantee about the
know there is no guarantee about the quality of the concepts. This is all
quality of the concepts. This is all
quality of the concepts. This is all natural language at this point and
natural language at this point and
natural language at this point and interesting possibility is to use some
interesting possibility is to use some
interesting possibility is to use some kind of a formal language to describe
kind of a formal language to describe
kind of a formal language to describe the the highle concepts.
the the highle concepts.
the the highle concepts. Now we also use this in a new discovery
Now we also use this in a new discovery
Now we also use this in a new discovery problem because we were u also worried
problem because we were u also worried
problem because we were u also worried about the possibility of this being an
about the possibility of this being an
about the possibility of this being an artifact of leakage in case of standard
artifact of leakage in case of standard
artifact of leakage in case of standard benchmarks like discovering fineman
benchmarks like discovering fineman
benchmarks like discovering fineman equations and so we used this uh method
equations and so we used this uh method
equations and so we used this uh method to come up with a new scaling law for
to come up with a new scaling law for
to come up with a new scaling law for LLMs and um so here what you see is um
LLMs and um so here what you see is um
LLMs and um so here what you see is um the so-called chinchila law so this is a
the so-called chinchila law so this is a
the so-called chinchila law so this is a law that was postulated in a deep mind
law that was postulated in a deep mind
law that was postulated in a deep mind paper from a few years back. And so here
paper from a few years back. And so here
paper from a few years back. And so here basically what you're trying to do is to
basically what you're trying to do is to
basically what you're trying to do is to predict the loss of the LLM, you know,
predict the loss of the LLM, you know,
predict the loss of the LLM, you know, based on um these various
based on um these various
based on um these various hyperparameters. And so this was the
hyperparameters. And so this was the
hyperparameters. And so this was the law. So you postulate a scaling law, you
law. So you postulate a scaling law, you
law. So you postulate a scaling law, you measure model loss with respect to
measure model loss with respect to
measure model loss with respect to hyperparameters and then you fit scaling
hyperparameters and then you fit scaling
hyperparameters and then you fit scaling law to data set. And in order to do
law to data set. And in order to do
law to data set. And in order to do this, of course, you would need to have
this, of course, you would need to have
this, of course, you would need to have a data set where you have a lot of
a data set where you have a lot of
a data set where you have a lot of values of these hyperparameters and
values of these hyperparameters and
values of these hyperparameters and corresponding uh accuracy values for the
corresponding uh accuracy values for the
corresponding uh accuracy values for the LLM. Now, we did the same thing with
LLM. Now, we did the same thing with
LLM. Now, we did the same thing with laser
laser
laser um rather than fitting a hand fitted law
um rather than fitting a hand fitted law
um rather than fitting a hand fitted law which was done in the in the chinchilla
which was done in the in the chinchilla
which was done in the in the chinchilla paper, right? So, they basically
paper, right? So, they basically
paper, right? So, they basically postulated a law like this and then they
postulated a law like this and then they
postulated a law like this and then they fit the parameters. But by contrast,
fit the parameters. But by contrast,
fit the parameters. But by contrast, what we did is that we just asked laser
what we did is that we just asked laser
what we did is that we just asked laser to go find it. And laser was able to
to go find it. And laser was able to
to go find it. And laser was able to come up with this sort of a law where um
come up with this sort of a law where um
come up with this sort of a law where um we also had this you know parameter
we also had this you know parameter
we also had this you know parameter called number of shots which is that if
called number of shots which is that if
called number of shots which is that if you're doing prediction you know what is
you're doing prediction you know what is
you're doing prediction you know what is the number of examples that you're
the number of examples that you're
the number of examples that you're giving it in context. Um and uh this in
giving it in context. Um and uh this in
giving it in context. Um and uh this in this parameter is available in some of
this parameter is available in some of
this parameter is available in some of these data sets right and so what we
these data sets right and so what we
these data sets right and so what we found is that there was this interesting
found is that there was this interesting
found is that there was this interesting kind of law that uh came up. Now this is
kind of law that uh came up. Now this is
kind of law that uh came up. Now this is just you know one example. It's not
just you know one example. It's not
just you know one example. It's not really uh very comprehensive yet but
really uh very comprehensive yet but
really uh very comprehensive yet but this just shows that you can make these
this just shows that you can make these
this just shows that you can make these kinds of new discoveries using using
kinds of new discoveries using using
kinds of new discoveries using using this uh law. And so basically if you
this uh law. And so basically if you
this uh law. And so basically if you interpret this, the way to think about
interpret this, the way to think about
interpret this, the way to think about it is that a large number of shots gives
it is that a large number of shots gives
it is that a large number of shots gives poor results for low capability models.
poor results for low capability models.
poor results for low capability models. But then once the models pass a
But then once the models pass a
But then once the models pass a capability threshold, then having more
capability threshold, then having more
capability threshold, then having more shots, right? And this is sort of a
shots, right? And this is sort of a
shots, right? And this is sort of a common sense linguistic interpretation
common sense linguistic interpretation
common sense linguistic interpretation of the law that came
of the law that came
of the law that came out. So
out. So
out. So um you know um you can also do something
um you know um you can also do something
um you know um you can also do something after this. So if you're thinking about
after this. So if you're thinking about
after this. So if you're thinking about thinking of yourself as an LL and
thinking of yourself as an LL and
thinking of yourself as an LL and scaling law person, you start with the
scaling law person, you start with the
scaling law person, you start with the chinchilla law from the previous paper
chinchilla law from the previous paper
chinchilla law from the previous paper and then you say okay you know maybe I
and then you say okay you know maybe I
and then you say okay you know maybe I should bring in this insight about shots
should bring in this insight about shots
should bring in this insight about shots into the chinchilla law combine the old
into the chinchilla law combine the old
into the chinchilla law combine the old chinchilla law with this new discovery
chinchilla law with this new discovery
chinchilla law with this new discovery that was made by laser and then you find
that was made by laser and then you find
that was made by laser and then you find that uh this modified chinchilla
that uh this modified chinchilla
that uh this modified chinchilla actually is able to do better than both
actually is able to do better than both
actually is able to do better than both the old chinchilla and also the the you
the old chinchilla and also the the you
the old chinchilla and also the the you know the laser itself and so this is
know the laser itself and so this is
know the laser itself and so this is kind of interesting that um and shows
kind of interesting that um and shows
kind of interesting that um and shows that you know this discovery process
that you know this discovery process
that you know this discovery process using LLM agents and this is very much
using LLM agents and this is very much
using LLM agents and this is very much an agent right this is not just a
an agent right this is not just a
an agent right this is not just a oneshot LLM you're using an LLM combined
oneshot LLM you're using an LLM combined
oneshot LLM you're using an LLM combined with this various other tools um and uh
with this various other tools um and uh
with this various other tools um and uh so what you are getting out of this
so what you are getting out of this
so what you are getting out of this is can influence human discovery as well
is can influence human discovery as well
is can influence human discovery as well and lead to something that is greater
and lead to something that is greater
and lead to something that is greater than the sum of the parts
than the sum of the parts
than the sum of the parts So in the interest of time I'm going to
So in the interest of time I'm going to
So in the interest of time I'm going to skip uh this next bit. Uh but uh what I
skip uh this next bit. Uh but uh what I
skip uh this next bit. Uh but uh what I said there is that these ideas can also
said there is that these ideas can also
said there is that these ideas can also be applied to settings where you have
be applied to settings where you have
be applied to settings where you have visual highdimensional inputs because
visual highdimensional inputs because
visual highdimensional inputs because now we have vision language models as
now we have vision language models as
now we have vision language models as well. So you can uh go crazy and and
well. So you can uh go crazy and and
well. So you can uh go crazy and and build these kinds of evolution based
build these kinds of evolution based
build these kinds of evolution based agents um where you have VLMs as part of
agents um where you have VLMs as part of
agents um where you have VLMs as part of the story. And uh I I'm extremely
the story. And uh I I'm extremely
the story. And uh I I'm extremely optimistic about uh this direction. So
optimistic about uh this direction. So
optimistic about uh this direction. So in summary, I would say that LLM
in summary, I would say that LLM
in summary, I would say that LLM directed evolution is a powerful tool
directed evolution is a powerful tool
directed evolution is a powerful tool for empirical science. And this point
for empirical science. And this point
for empirical science. And this point has already been made uh previously by
has already been made uh previously by
has already been made uh previously by fun search. But now you know we see that
fun search. But now you know we see that
fun search. But now you know we see that we can make it even more powerful with
we can make it even more powerful with
we can make it even more powerful with these um ideas of abstraction that are
these um ideas of abstraction that are
these um ideas of abstraction that are uh that that LLMs can give you basically
uh that that LLMs can give you basically
uh that that LLMs can give you basically for free. And uh even you know this can
for free. And uh even you know this can
for free. And uh even you know this can be even extended to visual settings
be even extended to visual settings
be even extended to visual settings where you have um to use now vision
where you have um to use now vision
where you have um to use now vision language models but hey they're coming a
language models but hey they're coming a
language models but hey they're coming a long way they have come a long way and
long way they have come a long way and
long way they have come a long way and uh importantly the abstraction abilities
uh importantly the abstraction abilities
uh importantly the abstraction abilities of LLMs can also be really helpful
of LLMs can also be really helpful
of LLMs can also be really helpful here open challenges you know
here open challenges you know
here open challenges you know verification of hypothesis and concepts
verification of hypothesis and concepts
verification of hypothesis and concepts concept representations that go beyond
concept representations that go beyond
concept representations that go beyond natural
natural
natural language scaling to larger search spaces
language scaling to larger search spaces
language scaling to larger search spaces input dimensions and then you even going
input dimensions and then you even going
input dimensions and then you even going beyond hypothesis generation to other
beyond hypothesis generation to other
beyond hypothesis generation to other parts of the scientific discovery
parts of the scientific discovery
parts of the scientific discovery process. But at the end though I am very
process. But at the end though I am very
process. But at the end though I am very optimistic
optimistic
optimistic that LLM agents not just LLMs but these
that LLM agents not just LLMs but these
that LLM agents not just LLMs but these kinds of agentic workflows where you
kinds of agentic workflows where you
kinds of agentic workflows where you have combinations of LLM
have combinations of LLM
have combinations of LLM queries as well as other kinds of
queries as well as other kinds of
queries as well as other kinds of machinery u they can be extremely
machinery u they can be extremely
machinery u they can be extremely powerful in scientific discovery. They
powerful in scientific discovery. They
powerful in scientific discovery. They can help you come up with new scientific
can help you come up with new scientific
can help you come up with new scientific hypothesis and uh even do experiment
hypothesis and uh even do experiment
hypothesis and uh even do experiment design and also as we saw in
design and also as we saw in
design and also as we saw in mathematical discovery they can be
mathematical discovery they can be
mathematical discovery they can be supremely powerful and again we are just
supremely powerful and again we are just
supremely powerful and again we are just in the early stages of uh what I think
in the early stages of uh what I think
in the early stages of uh what I think uh this research line of research will
uh this research line of research will
uh this research line of research will end up being. Um and this can have
end up being. Um and this can have
end up being. Um and this can have applications in uh in math, in science,
applications in uh in math, in science,
applications in uh in math, in science, in engineering as you saw the formal
in engineering as you saw the formal
in engineering as you saw the formal verification application, you know,
verification application, you know,
verification application, you know, building rigorous systems. Um so the
building rigorous systems. Um so the
building rigorous systems. Um so the future is is very bright. And with that,
future is is very bright. And with that,
future is is very bright. And with that, uh I'll end. I want to thank all my
uh I'll end. I want to thank all my
uh I'll end. I want to thank all my collaborators and funders. Uh, and I'm
collaborators and funders. Uh, and I'm
collaborators and funders. Uh, and I'm happy to take questions.